<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><Search><pages Count="112"><page Index="1"><![CDATA[DEPARTMENT OF FORENSIC SCIENCE
                         DEPARTMENT OF FORENSIC SCIENCE

                                         Bi- Annual Publication
                                   BI- ANNUAL PUBLICATION
































































                                             ISSN: 2583-7044 (Online)
                                               ISSN: 2583-7044 (Online)
                                                     Title: Veritas
                                                       Title: Veritas



                                                                                    Vol.4, Issue 1
                                                                                       Vol.4, Issue 1]]></page><page Index="2"><![CDATA[Message from the Principal































                                     Rev. Fr. Augustine George



      Forensic  Science  plays  a  pivotal  role  in          Veritas Volume:4, Issue 1
      the  criminal  justice  system  of  any                 The      Forensic        Science       newsletter,

      country.  As  it  deals  with  the  scientific          “Veritas”  is  a  bi-annual  newsletter

      examination  of  evidence,  it  makes  it               published  by  the  department  of  forensic
      more  valuable  in  assisting  the  court  to           science  which  compiles  articles  written

      make  the  correct  judgement.  Initiating              by  the  forensic  science  students  on

      from  the  scene  of  crime,  Forensic                  matters relating to Research Areas, Case
      Science  is  a  discipline  which  should  be           Studies,  Newer  Technologies  etc.  I  am

      highlighted  efficiently  throughout  the               happy  to  state  that  the  department  has
      process of criminal justice.                            procured  an  ISSN  number  for  the

      Forensic Science has evolved along with                 newsletter,       therefore        making        the

      science     in    the    implementation          of     newsletter  and  the  articles  in  it  more
      technology  to  aid  in  the  process  of               valuable.  This  edition  of  Veritas  will

      investigation  of  crime  and  analysis  of             ensure  to  bring  to  the  readers  more
      evidence.  Fields  like  Digital  Forensics             scientific  information  and  articles.  The

      have paved the way for investigation of                 faculty  and  students  of  the  department

      new age crimes.                                         have worked tremendously to ensure this
      The  Department  of  Forensic  Science  at              edition comes out well to its readers.

      Kristu  Jayanti  College  (Autonomous),                 On  this  occasion,  I  congratulate  the

      Bengaluru, has progressed very well and                 Department of Forensic Science and the
      in  the  fifth  year  of  their  existence  have        editorial  board  of  Veritas  for  the

      achieved  a  lot.  The  department  runs  a             successful and effective issue of the first

      bachelor’s (single major) & a bachelor’s                issue of the fourth volume.
      (double major).]]></page><page Index="3"><![CDATA[Message from the Dean


































                                         Dr. Calistus Jude A.L.



       It  is  a  delight  that  the  Department  of            This  edition  has  in  store  insightful

       Forensic Science, Kristu Jayanti College                 articles,  research  updates  and  reports
       has come out with its 4th Volume Issue                   of  the  myriad  programmes  organised

       1  of  the  newsletter  "Veritas".  This                 by  the  Department  of  Forensic

       edition  is  a  testament  to  the  dedication           Science.  The  flipbook  version  makes
       &  passion  of  the  students,  alumni  and              the  newsletter  more  interactive.  I

       faculty members of the department.                       congratulate        the     department        for
                                                                procuring an ISSN number for Veritas

       The      academic       community         of    the      which  makes  this  publication  more

       Department  consider  Veritas  as  a                     valuable.
       platform  to  showcase  the  research,

       acheivements and the contributions   of                  I  would  like  to  extend  my  heartfelt
       the department, its students and faculty                 gratitude  to  the  editorial  team,

       members.  It  reflects  the  impressive                  student  and  faculty  contributors  and

       growth of the department and highlights                  the  creative  team  who  have  worked
       the  role  played  by  the  students  and                tirelessly  to  bring  this  newsletter  to

       faculty  in  creating  awareness  on  the                fruition.  Their  efforts  have  truly

       latest trends in forensic science.                       captured the spirit and vibrancy of the
       I look forward to the continued growth                   department.

       and  success  of  the  department  and  the

       contributions  we  will  make  to  the  field
       of forensic science in the years to come.]]></page><page Index="4"><![CDATA[ADVISORY  BOARD







              FR. DR. AUGUSTINE GEORGE, PRINCIPAL.
              FR. DR. LIJO P THOMAS, VICE PRINCIPAL & CHIEF FINANCE

              OFFICER.
              FR. EMMANUEL P.J., DIRECTOR, KRISTU JAYANTI COLLEGE OF

              LAW, DIRECTOR, OFFICE OF INTERNATIONAL AND DOMESTIC
              RELATIONS.

              FR. JAIS V THOMAS, FINANCIAL ADMINISTRATOR, FACULTY
              DEPARTMENT OF COMMERCE AND MANAGEMENT.

              FR. SOM ZACHARIA, DIRECTOR, INFRASTRUCTURE PLANNING
              AND DEVELOPMENT.
              FR. JOSHY MATHEW, DIRECTOR, LIBRARY AND INFORMATION

              CENTRE, DIRECTOR, HR DEPARTMENT, HEAD, DEPARTMENT OF
              ENGLISH.

              FR. DEEPU JOY, DIRECTOR, STUDENT WELFARE OFFICE,
              FACULTY,  DEPARTMENT OF LIFE SCIENCES.

         EDITORIAL  BOARD




                                                     FACULTY



             PROF. DON CAEIRO, HEAD, DEPARTMENT OF FORENSIC SCIENCE

             PROF. SUCHITA RAWAT, ASSISTANT PROFESSOR, DEPARTMENT OF
             FORENSIC SCIENCE

             PROF. DEVI. S, ASSISTANT PROFESSOR, DEPARTMENT OF FORENSIC
             SCIENCE
             PROF. SHRISTI AICH, ASSISTANT PROFESSOR, DEPARTMENT OF

             FORENSIC SCIENCE
             PROF. MAYANK DAVID RAIBORDE, ASSISTANT PROFESSOR,

             DEPARTMENT OF FORENSIC SCIENCE
             PROF. NEHA VISHE, ASSISTANT PROFESSOR, DEPARTMENT OF

             FORENSIC SCIENCE
             PROF. ANNAPOORNI AMMAL, ASSISTANT PROFESSOR, DEPARTMENT

             OF FORENSIC SCIENCE
             PROF. VISMAYA, ASSISTANT PROFESSOR, DEPARTMENT OF
             FORENSIC SCIENCE

             PROF. RETTY MARY SHAJI, TEACHING ASSISTANT, DEPARTMENT OF
             FORENSIC SCIENCE]]></page><page Index="5"><![CDATA[EDITORIAL  BOARD




                                                STUDENTS





        REVIEW TEAM






















                             TEJASWINI T S  SIMEON HANESH   JENCY MATTHEW   SNEHA BEJOY
                             III Semester        DAS             SUNIL       III Semester
                                               V Semester      V Semester
          EDITING TEAM






















                  PRIYANKA GHOSH      SREEVIDYA       SNEHA M      ALLEN JOSE      GOURAV KUMAR
                     III Semester      REJITH        V Semester   TOMYACHEN          III Semester
                                      III Semester                  V Semester

   DESIGNING TEAM






















                        NAKISHISHA K      MALAVIKA       PEREPPADEN    DEBOLEENA   VARUN SAI S
                       MARBANIANG     GOPURATHINGAL       ANCILA         GUHA        V Semester
                         III Semester     III Semester   ROBINSON      III Semester
                                                         V Semester]]></page><page Index="6"><![CDATA[CONTENTS













                                      1.        DEPARTMENT ACTIVITIES









                                     2.         RESEARCH ARTICLES










                                     3. CASE STUDIES









                                    4. FEATURE ARTICLES








                                    5.          LITERATURE REVIEW










                                    6.          INFOGRAPHICS








                                      7.        CONTRIBUTORS]]></page><page Index="7"><![CDATA[E







                       P






                      A






                      R







                       T






                     M






                       E






                      N







                       T








            A C T I V I T I E S]]></page><page Index="8"><![CDATA[2



                    INTERNATIONAL CONFERENCE ON


                     ADVANCES IN FORENSIC SCIENCE


                                               (Hybrid mode)






         Date: 01/02/2024 TO 02/02/2024
         Number of beneficiaries:   In-house: 196                     External: 83

         List of Resource Persons with details:

         [Inauguration, Sessions and Valedictory]






































































                                        VERITAS VOLUME:4 ISSUE:1]]></page><page Index="9"><![CDATA[3



          DAY 1

          KEYNOTE SESSION 1
          TITLE: DIGITAL FORENSICS IN ARTIFICIAL INTELLIGENCE

          Resource Persons:

          Mr. Renju Varghese, VP of Forensics & R&D, SISA, Information Security, Bengaluru,
          India.



          Brief Write up

          On February 01, 2024, an insightful international guest lecture delved into the theme of

          "Digital  Forensics  in  Artificial  Intelligence."  Mr.  Renju  Varghese,  VP  of  Forensics  &
          R&D at SISA Bengaluru, India, served as the distinguished speaker for the occasion. His

          presentation provided a comprehensive overview of Sisa, a cybersecurity firm established

          in  2012,  known  for  conducting  over  1100  forensic  investigations  and  incident  response
          activities.  The  lecture  highlighted  Sisa's  utilization  of  GenAI  and  LLM  in  Digital

          Forensics and Incident Response (DFIR) operations, addressing pertinent topics such as

          ransomware  attacks,  API  integration,  emerging  cyber  challenges,  and  real-world
          corporate cases. Discussions also touched upon deep fake, voice phishing, supply chain

          threats, and adversaries leveraging LLM for cyber assaults. The session delved into the
          intricate investigative process of ransomware attacks, covering image and log acquisition,

          analysis,  standardization,  and  the  application  of  ML  models  for  fraud  detection.  The

          discourse concluded with an examination of the advantages and drawbacks of AI, insights
          into  unique  cases  handled  by  Sisa,  and  predictions  for  future  breach  scenarios.  An

          interactive Q&A session provided participants with an opportunity to delve deeper into
          the topics discussed, fostering a richer understanding of the subject matter.


































                                       VERITAS VOLUME:4 ISSUE: 1]]></page><page Index="10"><![CDATA[4





         DAY 1

         KEYNOTE SESSION 2

         TITLE: THE USE OF SOIL IN CRIMINAL INVESTIGATION
         Resource Persons:

         Prof. Lorna Dawson, Head, Forensic Soil Science, The James Hutton Institute, United

         Kingdom.



         Brief Write-up

         On February 01, 2024, an illuminating international guest lecture centered on the topic of
         Soil in Criminal Investigation. Professor Lorna Dawson, Head of Forensic Soil Science at

         The James Hutton Institute, United Kingdom, and leader of the Soil Forensics Group,
         delivered  a  comprehensive  discourse.  Her  presentation  explored  the  pivotal  role  of  soil

         analysis in guiding investigations, drawing insights from historical references such as the

         Romans  in  100  BC-400  BC,  Georg  Popp's  Filbert  Case  (1908),  and  the  principles
         articulated by Sir Arthur Conan Doyle in his Sherlock Holmes series, in correlation with

         Edmond Locard's Principle of Exchange. The lecture underscored the significance of soil-
         based  evidence  including  hair,  blood,  DNA,  diatoms,  and  pollen,  while  a  live

         demonstration of a missing person investigation shed light on the challenges faced in real-

         world  scenarios.  Prof.  Lorna  detailed  the  process  of  soil  evidence  search,  examinations
         such  as  GS-MS,  the  uncertainty  surrounding  soil  evidence,  and  its  integrity  as  court-

         admissible evidence. She shared personal experiences where soil analysis played a crucial

         role in identifying culprits and cautioned against its potential to mislead investigations.
         Emphasizing the need for foresight in outsmarting criminals, the lecture concluded with a

         poignant tribute to victims. The session not only upheld the integrity of the subject matter

         but also instilled a deeper sense of humanity and pursuit of justice.




























                                                                 4

                                                                   I
                                                            M
                                                               E
                                                                :
                                                                         E
                                                                           :
                                                                            1
                                                                    S
                                                                      S
                                                                       U
                                           R
                                             I
                                              T
                                       VERITAS VOLUME:4 ISSUE: 1
                                        V
                                          E
                                                A
                                                      O
                                                        L
                                                          U
                                                  S

                                                    V]]></page><page Index="11"><![CDATA[5




        ORAL PAPER & PAPER PRESENTATION
        Conducted  through  Zoom  with  10  panellists,  the  online  oral  paper  and  poster

        presentation  entailed  a  thorough  investigation  of  the  research  topic.  Participants

        underscored  the  study's  importance  and  its  relevance  within  its  field,  outlining  precise
        objectives  and  methodological  approaches.  Results  were  presented  with  meticulous

        attention,  utilizing  visual  aids  such  as  graphs  and  tables  for  enhanced  clarity.  The
        discussion critically assessed findings, placing them in context with existing literature and

        addressing  limitations.  The  presentation  concluded  by  summarizing  significant  insights

        and  proposing  future  research  directions  or  practical  applications.  Each  participant
        received individual scores from the panellists.






































































                                                                 4

                                                                   I
                                                            M
                                                               E
                                                                :
                                                                         E
                                                                           :
                                                                            1
                                                                    S
                                                                      S
                                                                       U
                                           R
                                             I
                                              T
                                       VERITAS VOLUME:4 ISSUE: 1
                                        V
                                          E
                                                A
                                                      O
                                                        L
                                                          U
                                                  S

                                                    V]]></page><page Index="12"><![CDATA[VERITAS VOLUME:4 ISSUE: 1                                                6




        DAY 2
        KEYNOTE SESSION 3

        TITLE:  FACES,  FINGERPRINTS  AND  BEYOND  THE  TIMELESS  NEED  FOR

        HUMAN IDENTIFICATION
        Resource Persons:

        Dr. Deepak V, Head, Department of Forensic Dentistry, MR, Ambedkar Dental College,
        Bengaluru, India




        Brief Write up
        On February 02, 2024, an insightful international guest lecture delved into the topic "Faces,

        Fingerprints,  and  Beyond:  The  Timeless  Need  for  Human  Identification."  Dr.  Deepak,

        Head  of  the  Department  of  Forensic  Dentistry  at  MR  Ambedkar  Dental  College,
        Bengaluru, India, served as the distinguished speaker. Dr. Deepak's lecture focused on the

        critical importance of human identification, particularly in disaster cases, emphasizing the

        role  of  dentistry  in  creating  individual  dental  profiles  for  victims.  He  highlighted
        collaborative  efforts  with  the  Department  of  Forensic  Medicine  to  solve  criminal  cases

        using  dental  and  skeletal  evidence,  notably  aiding  in  the  identification  of  victims  in  the
        'Orissa  Train  Accident.'  Dr.  Deepak  stressed  the  significance  of  dignified  body  disposal,

        advocating for "Dignity for the dead or else trauma for the living," and underscored the

        equal importance of justice for the deceased. He discussed the contributions of Forensic
        Anthropology in identification processes and outlined challenges specialists face, including

        difficulties in recognizing decomposed or charred faces, emotional stress leading to false
        identifications, and the complexities of victim identification in mass disasters. The session

        concluded  with  an  engaging  Q&A  segment,  allowing  attendees  to  seek  clarification  and

        deepen their understanding of the topics discussed.






























                                        VERITAS VOLUME:4 ISSUE:1]]></page><page Index="13"><![CDATA[VERITAS VOLUME:4 ISSUE: 1                                                7




        DAY 2
        KEYNOTE SESSION 4

        TITLE: POTENTIAL UTILITY IN FORENSIC ENTOMOLOGY

        Resource Persons:
        Dr.  L.  Shashikumar,  Scientific  Officer,  Biology  Section,  Regional  Forensic  Science

        Laboratory, Mysuru, India.



        Brief Write up

        Dr. L Shasikumar, the senior scientific officer at RFSL, Mysore, delivered an insightful
        lecture on the potential applications of forensic entomology. The lecture provided students

        with  valuable  knowledge  on  how  insects  contribute  to  forensic  investigations.  Various

        insects  crucial  to  estimating  post-mortem  intervals  (PMI)  were  discussed,  with  the  first
        recorded case dating back to the 13th century, reported by the Chinese (McKnight, 1981).

        Dr. Shasikumar emphasized that insects, being the dominant group on Earth, offer insights

        beyond PMI estimation. Forensic entomology enables the determination of the season and
        geographical location of death, as well as the identification of routes used by perpetrators.






















































                                        VERITAS VOLUME:4 ISSUE:1]]></page><page Index="14"><![CDATA[VERITAS VOLUME:4 ISSUE: 1                                                8





        ORAL PAPER & POSTER PRESENTATIONS

        ORAL PAPER PRESENTATION (OFFLINE) PANEL 1



        Brief Write up

        The offline presentations showcased the expertise of skilled and talented candidates who
        explored  various  aspects  of  future  research  in  forensic  science,  discussing  its  advantages

        and disadvantages. One notable research topic was "Sex and Region Estimation through
        Cephalic Index Data," which introduced a new identification strategy for future forensic

        applications. While sex estimation accuracy stood at 50%, region estimation (North/South

        Indian) accuracy was 43%. Two presentations delved into this topic, one focusing solely on
        South  Indian  data  and  the  other  comparing  North  and  South  Indian  states,  both

        suggesting the potential use of cephalic index in sex estimation in the future, albeit with

        questionable accuracy in region estimation due to limited sample heterogeneity.



        Another  standout  presentation  titled  "Chemometrics:  Bridging  Forensic  Spectral  Data

        Analysis with Data Science" highlighted the individualization of local vermilion samples
        from  Kerala  and  Karnataka.  Utilizing  Python  software  and  libraries  like  NumPy  and

        Pandas, the study explored the application of chemometrics in analysing mixed biological
        samples.  Successfully  predicting  the  purchase  location  of  vermilion,  this  research  offers

        promising implications for future forensic endeavours and inspires researchers in the field

        of Future Forensics.







































                                        VERITAS VOLUME:4 ISSUE:1]]></page><page Index="15"><![CDATA[VERITAS VOLUME:4 ISSUE: 1                                                9



        DAY 2

        KEYNOTE SESSION 5
        TITLE:  THE  ART  OF  TRUTH:  VIRTOPSY’S  DIGITAL  CANVAS  IN  FORENSIC

        INQUIRY



        Brief Write up

        On February 02, 2024, a captivating international guest lecture centered on the theme "The
        Art of Truth: Virtopsy’s Digital Canvas in Forensic Inquiry." Dr. S. K. Karthik, Professor

        and Head of the Department of Forensic Medicine and Toxicology at Dr. B.R.Ambedkar

        Medical College, Bengaluru, served as the distinguished speaker. Dr. Karthik commenced
        his presentation with an insightful overview of the history and fundamentals of autopsy,

        delving into traditional methods and their associated challenges. The discussion extended

        to various types of skin incisions, including I-shaped, Y-shaped, Modified Y-shaped, and
        T-shaped, commonly used in autopsies. Dr. Karthik then explored the concept of virtual

        autopsy, elucidating its applications in Thanatological investigation, Age estimation, Mass
        disaster cases, Skin lesion analysis, Gender identification, and more. He showcased images

        captured with a digital camera for Photogrammetry, explaining virtual autopsy techniques

        and the practical use of PACS - Picture Archiving and Communication System, a medical
        imaging  technology  facilitating  cost-effective  storage  and  easy  access  to  images  from

        various modalities like X-ray, MRI, CT scans, and ultrasound. The session concluded with
        a  comprehensive  examination  of  the  Advantages  and  Disadvantages  of  Virtual  autopsy,

        followed by an interactive Q&A segment, providing participants with an opportunity to

        pose questions and enhance their understanding of the discussed topics.




































                                        VERITAS VOLUME:4 ISSUE:1]]></page><page Index="16"><![CDATA[VERITAS VOLUME:4 ISSUE: 1                                               10




        Day -2
        VALEDICTION AND CERTIFICATE DISTRIBUTION

        Chief  Guest:  Dr.  Deepak  V,  Head,  Department  of  Forensic  Dentistry,  MR,  Ambedkar

        Dental College, Bengaluru, India
        Prof. Don Caeiro, Coordinator of Department of Forensic Science, Kristu Jayanti


        Brief Write up

        Mr.  Don  Caeiro,  the  Conveyer  of  the  INTERNATIONAL  CONFERENCE  ON

        ADVANCES IN FORENSIC SCIENCE (ICAFS) 2024, expressed his immense pleasure in
        welcoming esteemed dignitaries to the event. Among them were chief guest Dr. Vinod J.

        Lakkapan,  and  distinguished  guests  including  Mr.  Renju  Varghese,  VP  of  Forensic  &

        R&D,  SISA,  Information  Security  Bengaluru,  India;  Prof.  Lorna  Dawson,  Head  of
        Forensic Soil Science, The James Hutton Institute, United Kingdom; Dr. L Shashikumar,

        Scientific Officer, Biology Section, Regional Forensic Science Laboratory, Mysuru, India;

        and Dr. S. K. Karthik, Professor and Head of the Department of Forensic Medicine and
        Toxicology,  Dr.  B.  R.  Ambedkar  Medical  College  Bengaluru,  India.  He  also  extended

        gratitude  to  the  management  of  Kristu  Jayanti  College,  co-conveyors,  students,
        participants,  and  all  individuals  involved  in  ensuring  the  success  of  ICAFS  2024.  Dr.

        Deepak V, Head of the Department of Forensic Dentistry, MR Ambedkar Dental College

        Bengaluru,  presented  awards  for  the  best  Poster  and  Paper  presentations  in  both  online
        and offline modes, and distributed certificates to all participants of the event.









































                                        VERITAS VOLUME:4 ISSUE:1]]></page><page Index="17"><![CDATA[VERITAS VOLUME:4 ISSUE: 1                                               11

                   WORKSHOP ON DISASTER VICTIM



                                        IDENTIFICATION



         Date: 03/02/2024

         Details of participants: External Participants from various forensic science colleges
         Resource Persons:

         Dr. Deepak V, Head Department of Forensic Dentistry, MR Ambedkar Dental College,

         Bengaluru, India



         Brief Write up
         Disaster Victim Identification (DVI) is the process of identifying individuals who have died

         as  a  result  of  a  mass  casualty  incident  or  disaster.  This  process  is  crucial  for  various

         reasons,  including  providing  closure  to  the  families  of  the  deceased,  facilitating  legal
         proceedings,  and  aiding  in  the  management  of  disaster  response  efforts.  DVI  typically

         involves  a  multidisciplinary  approach,  drawing  upon  expertise  from  forensic  science,

         forensic dentistry, anthropology, pathology, DNA analysis, and other relevant fields. One-
         day post conference workshop on Disaster Victim Identification (DVI), organized by the

         department of forensic science turned out to be a very beneficial and eye-opening session

         for  the  participants  of  the  International  Conference  on  Advances  in  Forensic  Science
         (ICAFS’24) organized by the department and as well as for the PG students. The speaker

         for the workshop was Dr. Deepak V, C. Director, Department of Forensic Dentistry and
         Faculty,  Department  of  Oral  &amp;  Maxillofacial  Pathology  and  Microbiology,

         Coordinator, Internal Quality Assurance Cell, at M R Ambedkar Dental College &amp;

         Hospital Bengaluru, Karnataka, India. A total of 15 external participants witnessed and
         received a very insightful session on the proposed topic as well as had a great experience on

         the  outdoor  hands-on  practical  session  on  the  same  topic.  A  small  demonstration  of
         FTIR/ATR  situated  at  the  Forensic  Science  Research  unit  of  the  department  was  also

         conducted  for  the  external  participants  by  Dr.  Suchita  Rawat,  Assistant  Professor  and

         Research coordinator of the department at the end of the workshop.




















                                        VERITAS VOLUME:4 ISSUE:1]]></page><page Index="18"><![CDATA[VERITAS VOLUME:4 ISSUE: 1                                               12

           INTER-COLLEGIATE FEST - ‘INQUISITOR’







        Date: 20/02/2024

        Name  and  details  of  the  Resource  Person:  Major  Saurabh  Srivastava,  Director  (South

        Asia), Crisis and Security Consulting, Bengaluru.



        Brief Write up
        The  Forensic  Science  club,  Unit  of  Forensic  Science  organized  Inquisitor  2023,  inter-

        collegiate forensic fest for students of forensic science in other colleges based in India. This

        forensic fest aimed at discovering students’ knowledge and understanding of the subject as
        it offered a wide science related events.

        The event was organized by the student coordinators of the Forensic Science club at Kristu

        Jayanti College, Bangalore. The BSc Forensic Science students at Kristu Jayanti College
        formed the working group and were event and team organisers. The participants included

        the Forensic Science students from 4 different institutes across India.

        The fest was executed with a total of 7 events and was organized at its best of quality. The
        fest was conducted offline in the college campus. The high- spirited forensic fest started

        with preliminary rounds of various events on 20th February, 2024.
        The participants were given participant codes to ensure fairness and none of the internal

        students participated and the event was open only for external participants.



        The events held were:

        1.X-Word -A crossword event.
        2.Cross Examination - A case study presentation event.

        3.Crimetoonist - A sketching event.

        4.I-Witness - An observation game.
        5.Wiz Quiz - A Forensic Science quiz event.

        6.Room of Opinions - A debate event.

        7.Sherlock & Watson - A personality type contest with a forensic theme.



        The inaugural ceremony of the fest was presided over by Rev. Fr. Dr. Augustine George,

        Principal,  Kristu  Jayanti,  Kristu  Jayanti  College  and  the  chief  guest  was  Mr.  Saurabh
        Srivastava,  Director  (South  Asia),  Crisis  and  Security  Consulting,  Bengaluru.  In  his

        presidential address, Father enlightened about the importance of forensic science and its
        scope in everyday life.




                                        VERITAS VOLUME:4 ISSUE:1]]></page><page Index="19"><![CDATA[VERITAS VOLUME:4 ISSUE: 1                                               13




         Mr.  Saurabh  spoke  about  the  need  for  forensic  enthusiasts  to  be  in  touch  with
         everyday  happenings  and  to  look  out  for  advancements  in  the  field.  He  encouraged

         students  to  keep  upskilling  and  following  their  dreams  and  motivated  them  to  use

         opportunities  provided  during  such  fests  to  empower  themselves.  In  the  valedictory
         ceremony, Fr. Joshy Mathew, Director, Library and Information Centre Director, HR

         Department Head, Department of English, Kristu Jayanti College, Bangalore exhorted
         the students to keep trying and giving their best in fests such as this. Felicitation of the

         winners of various events and overall winners were announced.











































































                                        VERITAS VOLUME:4 ISSUE:1]]></page><page Index="20"><![CDATA[VERITAS VOLUME:4 ISSUE: 1                                               14

                GUEST LECTURE ON UPSKILLING IN



                                     FORENSIC SCIENCE






          Date: 23/02/2024

          Name and details of the Resource Person: Mr. Hemanth Kumar, Practising Advocate,

          High court and subordinate courts, Bangalore
          Objective:  To  provide  students  with  valuable  insights  into  the  diverse  career

          opportunities available in both the public and private sectors.



          Brief Write up

          The  guest  lecture  session,  led  by  Mr.  Hemanth  Kumar,  Mr.  Hemanth  Kumar,  a
          seasoned  advocate  practicing  in  high  courts  and  subordinate  courts  in  Bangalore,

          proved to be an invaluable opportunity for students. Mr. Kumar's insightful discourse

          transcended the boundaries of traditional career advice, delving into the multifaceted
          avenues available in both public and private sectors. Emphasizing the need for students

          to  transcend  textbook  knowledge,  he  advocated  for  active  networking  with

          professionals  to  gain  exposure  to  real-world  projects  and  research  endeavours.  Mr.
          Kumar's emphasis on staying abreast of market demands struck a chord, as he urged

          students to cultivate a proactive approach towards skill development. By encouraging
          students to explore additional courses and certifications, he paved the way for a more

          holistic  approach  to  career  advancement.  Furthermore,  Mr.  Kumar  highlighted  the

          indispensable  role  of  platforms  like  LinkedIn  in  facilitating  professional  networking
          and knowledge exchange. His words resonated with students, inspiring them to adopt a

          forward-thinking mind set and embrace continuous learning. The session empowered
          students to navigate the dynamic landscape of their respective fields with confidence

          and agility, armed with practical insights and a newfound sense of purpose.

























                                        VERITAS VOLUME:4 ISSUE:1]]></page><page Index="21"><![CDATA[VERITAS VOLUME:4 ISSUE: 1                                               15





              WORKSHOP ON MOBILE FORENSICS







         Date: 24/02/2024

         Venue: Conference Hall P2
         List of Resource Persons with details:























         Brief Write up

         Session  I:  SCOPE  AND  ACQUISITION  OF  ANDROID  AND  IOS  DEVICES,
         SOCIAL MEDIA FORENSICS




         Mr. Senthil Kumar who is the Chief Operating Officer of Proaxis Solutions addressed
         the gatherings on scope and acquisition of android and iOS devices and social media

         forensics. The topics which was addressed were:

             Android Forensics
           1. System, Architecture and Framework

           2. Linux Operating System

           3. Partitions in Android
           4. Toolkit plugins-Android data analysis(Android SDK, AVD, ADB)

           5. Advantages and Disadvantages of Rooting
           6. Implementation of System Architecture

             iOS Forensics

           7. File System
           8. Plist

           9. Acquisition  Methods  (iTunes  backup,  Logical  Acquisition,  Physical  Acquisition,
             Jailbreak Acquisition)






                                        VERITAS VOLUME:4 ISSUE:1]]></page><page Index="22"><![CDATA[VERITAS VOLUME:4 ISSUE: 1                                               16







          Session  II:  ACQUISITION  OF  MOBILE  DEVICES,  CALL  DETAIL  RECORD
          ANALYSIS, SIM CARD FORENSICS



          Ms.  Harini  Girish,  the  resource  person,  CEO  of  Proaxis  Solutions  conducted  a
          practical  session  with  hands-on  experience  on  acquisition  of  mobile  phone  devices

          using tools like Mobil Edit, Cellebrite UFED and also briefed about Magnet Acquire

          by  Magnet  Forensic.  She  explained  the  purpose  of  mobile  device  acquisition  and
          provided case scenarios to make the session more interactive. She also provided some

          great  insights  from  their  case  experiences  and  highlighted  some  stories  to  help  us
          appreciate  the  importance  of  the  topic.  Finally,  she  spoke  about  CDR  and  CDR

          Visualization tools, where we can acquire information about the summary of calls and

          other  essential  data  pertinent  to  the  case.  She  also  offered  a  unique  case  study
          regarding the importance of CDR and also pointed out the employment prospects in

          the field of forensics.
























































                                        VERITAS VOLUME:4 ISSUE:1]]></page><page Index="23"><![CDATA[VERITAS VOLUME:4 ISSUE: 1                                               17






                       KRYPTOS – FORENSIC SCIENCE



                                              EXHIBITION




          Date: 27/02/2024

          Details of participants:

          Students from different Higher secondary (PU) schools and colleges teaching forensic
          science and allied programmes (198)

          Students of the department of forensic science (518)

          Venue: M1 Audi, Main Block
          Resource Person:

          Major  Saurabh  Srivastava,  Director  (South  Asia),  Crisis  and  Security  Consulting,

          Bengaluru.



          Brief Write up
          Kryptos the forensic science exhibition was organized by the department of forensic

          science, Kristu Jayanti College on 20th February 2024. The exhibition garnered a lot of

          interest among students of the department and among nearby institutions.
          Major  Saurabh  Srivastava,  Director  (South  Asia),  Crisis  and  Security  Consulting,

          Bengaluru,  inaugurated  the  event  along  with  Fr.  Dr.  Augustine  George,  Principal,
          Kristu Jayanti College. During the inauguration the presidential address was delivered

          by Fr. Augustine George who stressed on the need for such events to improve the skill

          sets of students and he applauded the students and teachers of the department for the
          effort in organizing the exhibition.

          The  inaugural  address  was  delivered  by  Major  Saurabh  Srivastava,  Director  (South

          Asia),  Crisis  and  Security  Consulting,  Bengaluru,  who  explained  the  need  for
          exhibitions and how these events help in developing the psycho-motor skills and the

          experiential skills among students. He also exhorted the students to never stop learning

          and to keep the mindset of challenging defiance in times of uncertainty.
          A  total  of  105  chart  posters,  digitally  created  infographic  posters,  static  models,

          dynamic models were created by the students, and teachers of the department. A total
          of 11 institutions visited the exhibition during the day and gave very positive feedback.









                                        VERITAS VOLUME:4 ISSUE:1]]></page><page Index="24"><![CDATA[VERITAS VOLUME:4 ISSUE: 1                                               18



































































































                                        VERITAS VOLUME:4 ISSUE:1]]></page><page Index="25"><![CDATA[VERITAS VOLUME:4 ISSUE: 1                                               19





                               NATIONAL SCIENCE DAY







          Date: 28/02/2024

          Objective:
          The Deanery of Sciences at Kristu Jayanti College Autonomous organized a series of

          events  on  February  28th,  commemorating  National  Science  Day.  The  overarching

          theme for this year's celebration was 'Sustainable Future'. The objective was to engage
          students  in  exploring  and  understanding  the  significance  of  sustainable  practices  in

          shaping our future, particularly in the realm of science and technology.



          Brief Write up

          A series of events were organized to engage and inspire B.Sc. Forensic Science students
          across  different  years.  First-year  students  participated  in  a  'Trash  to  Treasure'

          competition, aimed at fostering creativity and environmental consciousness by making
          the  best  out  of  waste  materials.  For  second-year  students,  a  poster  presentation

          provided  a  platform  to  showcase  their  artistic  skills,  centered  around  the  theme  of

          sustainability.  Third-year  students  took  part  in  the  'Green  Energy  Clash'  debate
          competition,  which  encouraged  critical  thinking  and  discourse  on  various  aspects  of

          green energy and renewable solutions. Also, a guest lecture on arson investigation was

          conducted  for  M.Sc.  first  and  second-year  students  by  Mr.  Sandeep  Gujar,  offering
          valuable  insights  into  the  intricacies  of  arson  investigation  and  enhancing  their

          understanding of forensic science.

































                                        VERITAS VOLUME:4 ISSUE:1]]></page><page Index="26"><![CDATA[VERITAS VOLUME:4 ISSUE: 1                                               20




              INTERNATIONAL GUEST LECTURE ON


       QUALITY CONTROL IN FORENSIC SCIENCE





          Date: 16 /03/2024
          Resource Person: Ms Krishnendu Sreekumar, Quality Control Assistant in Xyfil ltd. In

          Preston, London.



          Brief Write up

          The expert lecture for the international lecture series for the academic year 2024 – 2025

          was  organized  by  the  Department  of  Forensic  Science,  Kristu  Jayanti  College,
          Autonomous on 16th march 2024 on the topic “quality control in forensic science”.

          The session was conducted online over the ZOOM platform.

          The lecture took place on 16th march 2024 and featured Ms Krishnendu Sreekumar, a
          prominent quality control assistant from XYFIL ltd. Preston, London. The main goal

          of the guest lecture was to offer students valuable insights into the swiftly expanding
          realm of quality control and assurance. This included discussing career opportunities

          within this field, as well as the essential skills needed for success.

          Ms Sreekumar began by introducing the concept of quality control and its significance
          in  today's  forensic  analysis.  She  highlighted  how  quality  control  involves  the

          identification, preservation, and analysis of products to prevent mishap in the future.
          The  speaker  elaborated  on  the  roles  and  responsibilities  of  a  quality  control

          professional.  She  discussed  how  these  experts  work  with  law  enforcement  agencies,

          corporations, and other organizations to ensure smooth analysis of the products before
          its launched in the market, and present their findings in a court of law. The speaker

          discussed the essential skills and qualifications required to pursue a successful career in

          quality control and toxicology.
          She  emphasized  on  abilities  such  as  expertise  in  toxicology,  laboratory  procedures,

          comprehension  of  operational  systems  and  products,  and  awareness  of  legal  and

          ethical aspects related to managing cosmetic products, all pertinent to roles in quality
          control.

          Ms.  Krishnendu  outlined  the  diverse  career  opportunities  available  in  the  field  of
          forensic  toxicology.  She  mentioned  roles  such  as  forensic  investigator,  incident

          responder, quality assurance specialist etc. She also discussed the potential for growth

          and specialization within the field. The session ended with an interactive question-and-
          answer round.

                                        VERITAS VOLUME:4 ISSUE:1]]></page><page Index="27"><![CDATA[VERITAS VOLUME:4 ISSUE: 1                                               21



































































































                                        VERITAS VOLUME:4 ISSUE:1]]></page><page Index="28"><![CDATA[VERITAS VOLUME:4 ISSUE: 1                                               22





               EXPERT LECTURE ON CYBER SAFETY



                           AWARENESS PROGRAMME-



                                     CYBER JAGROOKTA










         Date: 23 /03/2024
         Details  of  participants:  Faculty  of  Kristu  Jayanti  College,  Autonomous  and  Kristu

         Jayanti College of Law

         Resource Persons:
         Mr. Don Caeiro, Assistant Professor, Coordinator, Department of Forensic Science,

         Kristu Jayanti College.
         Objective: To provide faculty with safety tips while using cyberspace.



         Brief Write up
         The session focused on using cyberspace and information technology. Usage of social

         media,  QR  codes,  UPI  payments,  online  shopping,  and  installation  of  apps  were
         discussed in great detail. Several instances of crimes and attacks that have taken place

         in  the  past  were  also  discussed  and  more  emphasis  on  the  preventive  measures  that

         need to be taken by end users was deliberated. The session also threw light on the safe
         use of ATM and Credit cards and the various crimes that can take place with those

         kinds of crimes.































                                        VERITAS VOLUME:4 ISSUE:1]]></page><page Index="29"><![CDATA[VERITAS VOLUME:4 ISSUE: 1                                               23



































































































                                        VERITAS VOLUME:4 ISSUE:1]]></page><page Index="30"><![CDATA[VERITAS VOLUME:4 ISSUE: 1                                               24


                      WORKSHOP ON DETECTION OF



                                               DECEPTION







          Date: 17/04/2024
          Classes Attended & Number of beneficiaries: IV semester BSc Forensic science students

          and VI semester BA Psychology students

          Name  and  details  of  the  Resource  Person:  Mr.  Sunny  Joseph-Consultant  Clinical
          Psychologist & Neuropsychologist



          Brief Write up

          The  session  was  conducted  by  the  department  of  forensic  science  on  the  topic

          "Detection of Deception" to educate the students of IV semester BSc Forensic science
          and VI sem BA psychology. The resource person was well acquainted regarding the

          topic of the workshop. His knowledge and experience was shared with the students,

          increasing interest and knowledge in them. The workshop was conducted focusing on
          different aspects of deception detection. Sessions included lectures, group discussions,

          case  studies,  role-playing  exercises,  and  viewing  of  actual  detection  sessions  through

          videos. Participants had the opportunity to interact with experts in the field and receive
          knowledge about the field.










































                                        VERITAS VOLUME:4 ISSUE:1]]></page><page Index="31"><![CDATA[VERITAS VOLUME:4 ISSUE: 1                                               25



              GUEST LECTURE ON SEMINAR ON iOS



                            AND ANDROID FORENSICS









          Date: 18/04/2024

          Cyber Security Expert and Trainer, Indore, Madhya Pradesh
          Objective:

          The  objective  of  the  seminar  was  to  provide  students  with  insights  into  iOS  and

          Android forensic analysis, equipping them with practical skills and knowledge essential
          for mobile device forensics.



          Brief Write up

          On  April  18,  2024,  an  online  seminar  was  conducted  for  the  students  of  the  M.Sc.

          Forensic  Science  Program,  focusing  on  iOS  and  Android  forensic  analysis.  The
          seminar featured Prof. Gourav M. Rawal, a highly respected figure in the field of cyber

          security,  renowned  for  his  expertise  in  forensic  analysis.  With  over  a  decade  of

          experience and a national-level reputation, Prof. Rawal's contributions to the seminar
          were invaluable.

          The seminar encompassed a comprehensive exploration of various aspects of iOS and

          Android  forensic  analysis,  ranging  from  data  extraction  techniques  to  file  system
          analysis and application data recovery. Prof. Rawal leveraged his extensive knowledge

          to  delve  into  the  intricacies  of  mobile  device  forensics,  addressing  security
          considerations unique to these platforms. Through the incorporation of relevant case

          studies  and  examples,  Prof.  Rawal  illustrated  the  practical  applications  of  iOS  and

          Android  forensic  techniques  in  real-world  scenarios  such  as  criminal  investigations,
          digital forensics, and incident response.

          The seminar proved to be highly informative and beneficial for the students, providing
          them with a solid foundation in mobile device forensic analysis. Prof. Rawal's insights,

          coupled  with  the  interactive  nature  of  the  session,  facilitated  an  engaging  learning

          experience  for  all  attendees.  Overall,  the  seminar  served  its  objective  of  equipping
          students  with  valuable  insights  and  practical  skills  essential  for  navigating  the

          complexities of mobile device forensics in today's digital landscape.







                                        VERITAS VOLUME:4 ISSUE:1]]></page><page Index="32"><![CDATA[VERITAS VOLUME:4 ISSUE: 1                                               26

                      WORKSHOP ON INTELLECTUAL



                                      PROPERTY RIGHTS





          Date: 03/05/2024
          Venue: Conference Hall P1

          Mode: Offline
          Name  and  details  of  the  Resource  Person:  Mr.  Sanath  MV,  Founder,  Prasa  IP,

          Bengaluru

          Occasion- World IPR Day



          Brief Write up
          A Workshop on Intellectual Property Rights (IPR) was organised on 03/05/2024 by the

          Department  of  Forensic  Science  in  commemoration  of  World  IPR  Day.  Hosted

          offline, the session aimed to deepen understanding and awareness of the importance of
          IPRs and Patent Filing. Mr. Sanath MV, the Founder of Prasa IP, Bengaluru, graced

          the  occasion  as  the  keynote  speaker,  delivering  insights  and  perspectives  on  various

          facets  of  intellectual  property  and  process  for  filing  patents  and  related  clauses.  He
          delineated  the  various  forms  of  intellectual  property,  including  patents,  trademarks,

          copyrights, and trade secrets, elucidating their distinct features and legal implications.

          The  workshop  delved  into  the  legal  and  administrative  aspects  of  patent  filing,
          addressing common concerns and misconceptions among educators. Mr. Sanath MV

          provided insights into the role of patent attorneys, the importance of thorough prior
          art searches, and strategies for drafting comprehensive patent specifications.

           In addition to protection, the speaker underscored the potential benefits of patents in

          education, such as generating revenue through licensing agreements, attracting funding
          for research and development projects, and enhancing the reputation and marketability

          of educational institutions.
























                                        VERITAS VOLUME:4 ISSUE:1]]></page><page Index="33"><![CDATA[VERITAS VOLUME:4 ISSUE: 1                                               27







                          SEVEN-DAYS VIRTUAL FDP ON


                         EFFECTIVE TEACHER-STUDENT



                                              RELATIONSHIP







             Date: 06/06/2024 to 15/06/2024
             Venue: Zoom

             Time: 03:00 pm

             List of Resource Person:
































































                                        VERITAS VOLUME:4 ISSUE:1]]></page><page Index="34"><![CDATA[VERITAS VOLUME:4 ISSUE: 1                                               28


          Brief Write up

          Inaugural session of FDP Effective Student-Teacher Relationship
          The Faculty Development Program (FDP) on "Effective Student-Teacher Relationship"

          commenced on 06/06/2024 at 02:30 PM with an enriching inaugural session. The event

          witnessed  the  participation  of  distinguished  guests,  faculty  members,  and  enthusiastic
          educators,  all  eager  to  explore  the  dynamics  of  nurturing  fruitful  student-teacher

          relationships. The session started with a prayer which evoked God's blessing.

          Welcome speech was given by Mr. Don Caeiro, Coordinator, Department of Forensic
          Science, Kristu Jayanti College. All the chief guest and teachers and participants were

          welcomed by sir.

          The  prelude  for  the  inauguration  was  given  by  Ms.  Neha  Vishe,  Assistant  Professor,
          Department  of  Forensic  Science,  Kristu  Jayanti  College.  An  entire  summary  of  the

          upcoming sessions were given and set a start to the faculty development program. Ms.
          Vishe emphasized the importance of fostering positive interactions between students and

          teachers,  highlighting  how  these  relationships  contribute  significantly  to  the  overall

          learning environment and academic success.
          The presidential address was delivered by Father Deepu Joy, Director-Students Welfare,

          Kristu  Jayanti  College.  Father,  in  his  speech,  highlighted  the  moral  and  ethical
          dimensions  of  the  student-teacher  relationship.  He  stressed  the  role  of  empathy,

          understanding,  and  respect  in  cultivating  a  classroom  atmosphere  where  students  feel

          valued and motivated.
          After  the  presidential  address,  Ms.  Devi  S,  gave  a  brief  introduction  about  the  chief

          guest of the session Dr. Shanti Iyer. It was followed by the inaugural address by Dr.

          Shanti Iyer. Ms. Iyer emphasised on the importance of the subject of the FDP. Ma’am
          explained how teaching practices have a wide variety of challenges. Ma’am also talked

          about  the  effective  relationship  that  should  be  there  between  the  students  and  the

          teachers.
          The  inaugural  session  concluded  with  a  heartfelt  vote  of  thanks  delivered  by  Ms.

          Vismaya  Sr.  Ms.  Vismaya  expressed  gratitude  to  all  the  dignitaries,  participants,  and
          organizers  for  their  contributions  and  support  in  making  the  event  a  success.  She

          acknowledged the valuable insights shared and encouraged the participants to actively

          engage in the upcoming sessions of the FDP.
          The  inaugural  session  of  the  Faculty  Development  Program  on  "Effective  Student-

          Teacher Relationship" set a positive and inspiring tone for the subsequent sessions. The
          participants  left  with  a  renewed  sense  of  purpose  and  a  deeper  understanding  of  the

          pivotal role that effective student-teacher relationships play in the educational journey.



                                        VERITAS VOLUME:4 ISSUE:1]]></page><page Index="35"><![CDATA[VERITAS VOLUME:4 ISSUE: 1                                               29



            Day 1: Decoding GenZ: Insights into their Psychology and Behaviour

            Topic: Decoding GenZ: Insights into their Psychology and Behaviour

            Resource  person:  Mr.  Vigraanth  Bapu  K,  PG  Programme  Coordinator  and
            Assistant  professor,  Department  of  Psychology,  Kristu  Jayanti  College,

            Autonomous, Bengaluru



            Brief Write up

            The FDP session commenced with a brief introduction of the speaker by Ms. Devi

            S.  The  session,  titled  "Decoding  GenZ:  Insights  into  their  Psychology  and
            Behaviour,"  was  led  by  Mr.  Vigraanth  Bapu  K  G,  Assistant  Professor  and  PG

            Programme  Coordinator,  Department  of  Psychology,  Kristu  Jayanti  College,
            Bangalore.  Mr.  Vigraanth  provided  an  in-depth  exploration  of  Generation  Z,

            commonly  referred  to  as  Gen  Z.  He  delved  into  their  unique  psychological  traits

            and  behaviours,  shedding  light  on  how  this  generation  perceives  the  world.  The
            session  offered  valuable  insights  for  educators  and  professionals  to  better

            understand and engage with Gen Z effectively.



            Day 2: Teachers role in Student’s Mental Health

            Topic: Teachers role in Student’s Mental Health

            Resource  person:  Dr.  Richard  Jonas,  Professor  and  Head,  Department  of  Social
            Work,  Director-  Centre  of  Life  Skills  Education  (CLSE),  Kristu  Jayanti  College,

            Bangalore



            Brief Write up

            The  session  started  at  3  PM  with  a  silent  prayer.  The  MC  for  the  day  was  Mr.
            Mayank  David  Raiborde,  Assistant  Professor,  Department  of  forensic  science,

            Kristu  Jayanti  College.  Mr.  Mayank  introduced  briefly  about  the  various

            achievements of the speaker. The session was then carried forward by the speaker
            Dr.  Richard  Jonas,  Professor  and  Head,  Department  of  Social  Work,  Director-

            Centre  of  Life  Skills  Education  (CLSE),  Kristu  Jayanti  College,  Bangalore.  The

            speaker  initiated  the  talk  by  introducing  the  meanings  of  various  emoji’s  and
            abbreviations used by today’s students. A survey was taken in between to identify

            the emotional wellbeing of the participants. The role of teachers in student’s mental

            health was dealt with in detail. The session ended at 4 PM. All the participants were
            happy and they conveyed it through chat box




                                        VERITAS VOLUME:4 ISSUE:1]]></page><page Index="36"><![CDATA[VERITAS VOLUME:4 ISSUE: 1                                               30





            Day 3: Mentoring and Counselling skills

            Topic: Mentoring and Counselling skills

            Resource  person:  Dr.  T  S  Chandrashekara,  Faculty  and  Consultant  (Psychiatric
            Social  Work/Counselling),  Spandana  Nursing  Home  and  Rehabilitation  Centre,

            Bangalore



            Brief Write up

            The session for the day started at 3 pm with a silent prayer. The MC for the day was

            Ms.  Vismaya  S  R,  Teaching  assistant,  Department  of  Forensic  Science,  Kristu
            Jayanti College. A brief introduction about the speaker was given by Ms. Vismaya.

            It was followed by the session by the speaker of the day, Dr. T S Chandrashekara.

            Sir told that the session will be mainly based on his experience rather than theory.
            He explained about the various cases he encountered and how he handled them. The

            session  was  effective  and  highly  useful.  At  the  end  of  the  session  Ms.  Vismaya
            thanked the speaker and ended the session.






            Day 4: Reach before you Teach

            Topic: Reach before you Teach

            Resource person: Dr. Joseph Charles Tamilmaran D, Head, School of Management,
            Kristu Jayanti College, Bangalore




            Brief Write up
            The session for the day started with a silent prayer. The MC for the day was Ms.

            Shristi Aich, Assistant Professor, Department of Forensic Science, Kristu Jayanti
            College, Bangalore. Ms. Shisti gave a brief introduction about the speaker of the

            day. And the session was given for the speaker to carry forward. Dr. Joseph Charles

            Tamilmaran explained about the various methods by which a teacher can reach the
            students.  The  speaker  emphasised  on  the  importance  of  engaging  students  who

            belong to Gen Z. he also explained about the various methods that can be used by

            the teacher during pre course. He also emphasised on the importance of a teacher
            changing the current and conventional practises, to an interesting approach. It was

            followed by a question and answer session. The session was winded by thanking the

            speaker.




                                        VERITAS VOLUME:4 ISSUE:1]]></page><page Index="37"><![CDATA[VERITAS VOLUME:4 ISSUE: 1                                               31






            Day 5: Prosocial classroom for Effective Learning Goals

            Topic: Prosocial Classroom for Effective Learning Goals
            Resource person: Dr. Kumaravel, Professor and Head, Department of Social Work,

            Rajiv Gandhi National Institute of Youth Development



            Brief Write up

            The session started with a silent prayer and warm welcome by Ms. Nandini Katare,
            Assistant Professor, Department of Forensic Science, Kristu Jayanti College. Ms.

            Nandini, briefly introduced the speaker of the day to the participants and handed

            over the platform to the speaker. The speaker of the day Dr. Kumaravel, started the
            presentation by introducing the problems teachers face in the classroom. Later he

            continued  to  introduce  various  goals  we  should  follow  for  effective  learning.
            Various  classroom  management  styles  were  explained  to  promote  prosocial

            classrooms. A question answer session was conducted to clarify the doubts of all the

            participants. The session ended with a note of thanks towards the participants and
            the speaker of the day.






            Day 6: Teacher Ethics and Values

            Topic: Teacher Ethics and Values

            Resource person: Dr. Shanti Iyer, Former Principal and Advisor, Dr. NSAM First
            Grade College, NITTE Group Institutions, Bangalore.




            Brief Write up
            The  session  started  with  a  silent  prayer  and  warm  welcome  by  Ms.  Retty  Mary

            Shaji, Teaching Assistant, Department of Forensic Science, Kristu Jayanti College.

            Ms. Retty, briefly introduced the speaker of the day to the participants and handed
            over the platform to the speaker. The speaker of the day Dr. Shanti Iyer, started the

            presentation by introducing the importance of ethics and value in teaching. Later
            she explained with case studies the importance of ethics and values among teachers.

            A  question  answer  session  was  conducted  to  clarify  the  doubts  of  all  the

            participants. The session ended with a note of thanks towards the participants and
            the speaker of the day.







                                        VERITAS VOLUME:4 ISSUE:1]]></page><page Index="38"><![CDATA[VERITAS VOLUME:4 ISSUE: 1                                               32





            Day 7: Innovative Teaching Practices for Student Engagement
            Topic: Innovative Teaching Practices for Student Engagement

            Resource person: Dr. M Mathew Arumai, Assistant Professor, Department of Social

            Work, SRM Institute of Science and Technology, Kattankulathur.



            Brief Write up

            The session started with a silent prayer and warm welcome by Dr. Suchita Rawat,
            Assistant  Professor,  Department  of  Forensic  Science,  Kristu  Jayanti  College.  Dr.

            Suchita, briefly introduced the speaker of the day to the participants and handed
            over the platform to the speaker. The speaker of the day Dr. M Mathew Arumai,

            started the presentation by introducing the importance of the topic of the day. Later

            he explained various practices with which we can engage the students in the class,
            like conducting debate, quizzes, and all. A question answer session was conducted

            to clarify the doubts of all the participants. The session ended with a note of thanks
            towards  the  participants  and  the  speaker  of  the  day.  A  valedictory  session  was

            conducted in the end.





















































                                        VERITAS VOLUME:4 ISSUE:1]]></page><page Index="39"><![CDATA[E








                          S








                         E









                         A








                         R








                         C








                        H














          A R T I C L E S]]></page><page Index="40"><![CDATA[34
                                            PRESERVATION OF

         AUTHOR: SRI INEYA K
                                            BIOLOGICAL SAMPLES

                                            USING NANOTECHNOLOGY





                                             INTRODUCTION


       DID YOU                               The  biological  evidence  found  at  a  crime  scene  plays  a


       KNOW ??                               significant  role  in  establishing  a  connection  between  the
                                             suspect, the victim, and the crime scene. DNA and RNA
             Studies show that
                                             analysis  can  be  done  on  most  of  the  biological  evidence,
      nanoparticles can work their
        way into the bloodstream,            and  it’s  important  to  preserve  the  biological  samples
      penetrate cells, and get past          adequately to ensure their reliability.

         the blood-brain barrier.
        Research has linked such             Common  Preservation  Techniques  and  Liquids  Used  to
      particles to lung damage; the
                                             Preserve Biological Samples
       brain may be affected too.

                                             FORMALIN:  Usually  a  10%  formalin  solution  or  4%

       Nanotechnology  is  the               formaldehyde  gas  dissolved  in  water  is  used  to  preserve
       science  and  engineering  of         tissue  samples,  particularly  in  histology  and  pathology.

       manipulating matter at the            They  act  by  fixing  tissues  by  cross-linking  the  proteins,

       atomic      and      molecular        thereby  preventing  decay  and  maintaining  the  cellular
       scale,  typically  between  1-        structure.  It  is  highly  toxic  and  can  cause  various  health

       100  nm.  It  is  helping  to         issues.  It  can  alter  the  DNA/RNA  present  in  the  sample,

       improve  and  revolutionize           making it difficult to perform DNA/RNA analysis.
       many  sectors,  including             ETHANOL:  Used  in  a  concentration  of  70–100%  to

       information        technology,        preserve biological specimens like insects, tissues, and plant

       medicine,  climate  change,           materials.  It  dehydrates  the  tissues  and  kills  the
       security,     transportation,         microorganisms present in them. It can cause shrinkage and

       food                   security       hardening  of  the  tissues,  and  the  high  concentration  of
       environmental science, and            ethanol  can  alter  the  nucleic  acids  present  in  the  sample,

       forensic  science.  In  this          making it difficult for DNA extraction.

       article,    let's   see    how        BUFFER  SOLUTIONS:  Contains  sodium  chloride,
       nanotechnology  can  be               sodium phosphate, and potassium phosphate and is used to

       used to preserve biological           maintain  the  physiological  pH  of  biological  samples.  It  is
       samples  and  how  effective          suitable  for  cell  culture  and  molecular  biological

       it is.                                applications.




                                       VERITAS VOLUME:4 ISSUE: 1]]></page><page Index="41"><![CDATA[35



      It  can  be  used  for  DNA,  RNA,  and                Nanotechnology based preservatives
      protein assays. It can dilute blood samples,

      which       affects      the       concentration       The possible constituents of nanotech-based
      measurements, and is not suitable for long-            preservatives are

      term  preservation  since  it  cannot  prevent

      microbial growth.                                        1. Polymers: polyacrylamide/agarose, which
                                                                  enhances the preservative’s mechanical

      CRYPTOPROTECTANTS: One common                               properties and maintains the sample
      example  is  glycerol,  which  is  used  to                 integrity.

      preserve  cells  and  tissues  during  freezing          2. Anticoagulants: EDTA, sodium

      from ice crystal formation. It can be toxic                 citrate/heparin, which prevents the clotting
      to  cells  at  high  concentrations  and  can               of liquid samples.

      affect cell viability and integrity.                     3. Stabilizers: Glycerol/polyethylene glycol to

                                                                  enhance stability.
      RINGER'S  SOLUTION:  It  preserves                       4. Buffers: phosphate buffered saline (PBS) /

      tissues and organs by maintaining osmotic                   Tris buffer, which helps to maintain the

      balance. It helps preserve cellular functions               sample’s pH.
      for  short  periods.  It  cannot  prevent  long-         5. Preservatives: sodium azide / antimicrobial

      term degradation and microbial growth.                      agents to prevent microbial growth.
                                                               6. Silica nanoparticles: provide a porous

      EDTA (Ethylenediaminetetraacetic acid): It                  network that helps in the stabilization of

      prevents  the  clotting  and  degradation  of               proteins and nucleic acids.
      blood  samples  as  it  chelates  calcium  ions          7. Metal oxide nanoparticles: titanium oxide

      necessary for blood clotting. It is useful for              and zinc oxide, which act as antimicrobial
      many blood tests, including hematological                   agents and preserve the sample.

      assays  and  DNA  analysis,  but  can  affect            8. Silver nanoparticles: They maintain

      calcium  measurements  and  some  enzyme                    sterility and prevent microbial
      assays.  Long  storage  can  lead  to  DNA                  contamination.

      degradation and can dilute blood samples.                9. Gold nanoparticles: They offer unique

                                                                  interactions with biomolecules and assist
      SODIUM          FLUORIDE:           It    inhibits          in preservation.

      glycolysis  and  preserves  the  glucose  levels        10. Magnetic nanoparticles: Used to facilitate

      in  the  blood.  It  can  interfere  with                   easy separation or concentration of
      biochemical         assays,        and        high          specific components and allow for

      concentrations  are  toxic  to  cells  and  can             selective capture of biomolecules.
      affect DNA tests and some analysis.




                                       VERITAS VOLUME:4 ISSUE: 1]]></page><page Index="42"><![CDATA[36

      These  nanotech  preservatives  bind  to  the  cells,            CONCLUSION

      remove  the  moisture,  and  encapsulate  them.  The

      process  fixes  and  preserves  the  nucleic  acids,             Though  these  kinds  of  preservatives
      proteins, and cellular components. It maintains the              are        more         effective        and

      integrity  of  the  samples  until  they  are  taken  for        environmentally        friendly,      it    is

      analysis.  The  samples  can  be  preserved  in  these           important        to      consider       their
      liquids or gels for a longer period without freezer              complexity and cost-effectiveness also.

      or  liquid  nitrogen.  It  is  adaptable  to  preserve           Still,  nanotechnology  is  a  developing

      different  kinds  of  biological  samples,  ambient              field, and since evidence collection is a
      temperature,  and  storage  conditions.  They  are               process  of  greater  importance,  the

      non-toxic solutions, non-carcinogenic, and a safer               effectiveness  of  nanotechnology  in
      alternative  to  formalin  due  to  their  environment           that  process  is  still  a  question  mark

      and  user-friendly  approach.  Different  kinds  of              and  can  only  be  applied  if  its

      analysis,  such  as  DNA,  RNA,  and  Protein                    disadvantages       are     improved       by
      analysis,  PCR,  next-generation  sequencing,  and               further in-depth research. The cost of

      ELISA  can  be  done  by  preserving  the  sample  in            these advanced materials might pose a
      these  nanotech  preservatives.  These  preservatives            problem        for      small       forensic

      are stable at room temperature for a longer period.              laboratories  and  agencies.  Ethical

      Some of the commonly used preservatives require                  concerns       about      the      use     of
      safe    disposal      (like   deactivating       them     by     nanoparticles,  particularly  in  forensic

      neutralizing  them  before  disposing  of  them),                science, could pose obstacles. Overall,

      whereas nanotech preservatives can be disposed of                research  has  to  be  done,  and
      directly as they are non-toxic.                                  nanoscience  should  be  made  more

                                                                       cost-effective  and  reliable  to  make  it
     SAFE          HANDLING               AND          SAMPLE
                                                                       more  effective  and  applicable  in
     COLLECTION
                                                                       forensic science.


       1.  Any type of frozen sample should not be added
          to the preservative solution.

       2. Small  organs  and  tissues  can  be  preserved
          without slicing.

       3. Fresh blood and saliva can be directly added to

          the preservative since it won't alter the nucleic
          acids present in it.

       4. Plant materials can be directly submerged in the
          solution.

       5. It  is  inflammable,  so  it  should  be  handled

          carefully under high temperatures.

                                       VERITAS VOLUME:4 ISSUE: 1]]></page><page Index="43"><![CDATA[37





         REFERENCES



              InstaPRESERVE®                –       Migene.         (n.d.).

              https://www.migene.in/product/instapreserve-rt/



              Bajpai, V. K., Kamle, M., Shukla, S., Mahato, D.

              K., Chandra, P., Hwang, S. K., Kumar, P., Huh,
              Y. S., & Han, Y. (2018). Prospects of using

              nanotechnology for food preservation, safety, and

              security. Journal of Food and Drug Analysis,
              26(4), 1201–1214.

              https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jfda.2018.06.011



              Remington, K. (2022). Preservation of Biological

              Samples for Forensic Analysis. Journal of Forensic
              Sciences, 67(4), 1241-1253.



              Sharma, A., & Sharma, S. (2018). Nanoparticles in

              Biomedical Applications. Journal of Biomedical

              Nanotechnology, 14(10), 1721-1731.










































                                       VERITAS VOLUME:4 ISSUE: 1]]></page><page Index="44"><![CDATA[38
                                            COPYCAT CRIMINALS: A
        AUTHOR: DEBOLEENA


                   GUHA                     PHENOMENON OF CRIME


                                            IMITATION




                                            INTRODUCTION
      DID YOU


      KNOW ??                               A criminal born from exposure to prior publicized crime
                                            cases  or  a  fictional  portrayal,  now  known  as  "Copycat

           Crime often starts as            Criminals,"  has  always  been  a  demanding  theory  in  the
          more immitative than              field of forensic psychology and mass media. From serial
        innovative. A synthesis of          killings,  school  shootings,  and  arson  cases  to  terrorism,
        immitative and innovative           etc., the copycat crime is a conjugation of two factors: a
        crime together creates a
                                            motivated  perpetrator  to  commit  the  crime  and  the
            “Crime Evolution”
                                            influence  of  "generator  crime,"  majorly  impacting  the
                                            modus operandi.


                                             Cases of Copycat Crimes
      Generator  Crime  is  prior

      criminogenic              content      Jack the Ripper Copycat
      accounted  for  by  the  media         The earliest acknowledged crime to be imitated was on the

      that acts as the precursor for         unidentified serial killer of London in 1888. Jack the Ripper

      the  copycat  phenomenon.              was  known  for  brutally  murdering  prostitutes  in  the
      Although  many  theories               Whitechapel area in a particular method of mutilation. 120

      exist  on  crime  imitation            years later, Derek Brown imitated the exact methodologies
      through       the    ages,     the     to choose his victims. Although no body was found, Derek

      concept         was        widely      was convicted of six cases of sexual assault and mutilation

      popularized  through  media            in the Whitechapel prostitution area.
      in the 1970s and '80s. In the

      1961  New  York  Times                 Zodiac copycat
      publicised  article  "Case  of         During the 1960s, the infamous case of the Zodiac Killer of

      the  Copycat  Criminals,"              the  San  Francisco  area  was  a  media  sensation.  The  serial

      David Dressler brought this            killer  gained  his  attention  for  taunting  the  police  and
      term to the limelight. Soon,           criminal  justice  system  through  cryptic  letters.  He  was

      copycat       criminals      were      known  to  have  selective  victims  relating  to  their  zodiac

      distinguished  as  a  separate         signs. Although his identity remained unknown to date, 20
      class of offenders.                    years  later,  Heriberto  "Eddie"  Seda  began  the  exact

                                             imitation of the serial killing in New York.


                                       VERITAS VOLUME:4 ISSUE: 1]]></page><page Index="45"><![CDATA[39



       Seda  even  mimicked  the  Zodiac  Killer's                  Tylenol Killer Copycat
       signature  method  of  sending  cryptic  letters  to         In  1982,  the  Food  and  Drug

       the  newspaper  office.  His  copycat  spree                 Administration        (FDA)      faced     an

       continued  for  the  subsequent  3  years  until  he         emergent situation when seven people
       was convicted in 1996.                                       around  the  Chicago  area  died  after

                                                                    consuming  Extra-Strength  Tylenol

       School Shooting Copycat                                      adulterated  with  cyanide.  The  FDA
       On  April  20,  1999,  two  students  of  the                established  the  law  that  all  over-the-

       Columbine High School (Colorado) reportedly                  counter  drugs  should  be  sold  in

       murdered  12  students  and  1  teacher  through             tamper-resistant  packages,  but  the
       open  shooting.  The  perpetrators  were  twelfth            panic  had  already  manifested  among

       graders,  Eric  Harris  and  Dylan  Klebold,  who            American  citizens.  Waves  of  copycat
       later  committed  suicide  after  carrying  out  the         crimes  were  seen  following  this

       attack.  This  incident  marked  a  new  popular             incident  to  exploit  this  fear  and

       culture  of  crime,  now  termed  the  Columbine             mislead.  Cases  of  product  tampering
       Effect. The first probable copycat crime of this             spiked, and in the year 1982 alone, the

       incident  was  the  W.  R.  Myers  High  School              FDA handled 36 incidents of hardcore
       shooting in Alberta, just 8 days later. Over the             tampering,  according  to  David  P.

       time  from  1992  to  2024,  there  have  been  70+          Mikkelson’s  article  “Horrors:  Tylenol

       copycat crimes in this manner across America                 Murders." One of the famous copycats
       and Europe.                                                  “Tylenol  laced  with  cyanide  killings”

                                                                    was in 1986, when a woman reported

                                                                    her husband’s death on taking Extra-
                                                                    Strength      Tylenol.     However,       the

                                                                    accusation on the medicine brand was

                                                                    abandoned  when  the  investigators
                                                                    found  the  woman,  Stella  Nickell,

                                                                    guilty  of  tampering  with  the  Tylenol
                                                                    with  cyanide.  In  this  case,  the

                                                                    imitation of the crime was simply done

                                                                    to mislead the investigators.



               Image 1: Columbine High School massacre
               surveillance footage









                                       VERITAS VOLUME:4 ISSUE: 1]]></page><page Index="46"><![CDATA[40

                                                                      Acid attack copycat

                                                                      On  April  28th,  2022,  a  woman  was

                                                                      attacked by throwing acid while going
                                                                      to  work  near  Magadi  Road,  West

                                                                      Bengaluru.  The  perpetrator  was

                                                                      reported  to  be  Nagesh  Babu,  whom
                                                                      she  rejected  for  marriage.  Such  cases

                                                                      of  acid  attacks  by  jilted  lovers  have
                                                                      become  a  popular  copycat  crime

                                                                      culture.  A  study  conducted  on  acid
              Image 2: “Scream” copycat Thierry Jaradin
                                                                      attacks  in  India  from  2009  to  2013
      "Scream" copycat                                                showed that in the majority 18.96% of

      The imitation of crime is not confined to real-life             these  cases,  the  offender  was  a  jilted
      incidents.  Its  inspiration  can  be  drawn  from              lover.  In  74.13%  of  incidents,  the

      works  of  fiction  as  well.  Such  was  the  murder           victim  personally  knew  the  offender.

      case of 15-year-old Allison Cambier (Gerpinnes,                 This  imitative  crime  of  "jilted  lover
      2001). The offender, Thierry Jaradin, put on the                acid  attacks"  has  only  increased  in

      costume of the movie "Scream" and stabbed his                   recent years.

      victim  30  times  after  she  refused  his  sexual
      advances. Jaradin openly confessed to the crime                 Therioes of copycat phenomenon

      and the influence of the movie.

                                                                      Although  there  is  no  one  particular
     “Dhoom” robbery copycat
                                                                      reason  for  the  occurrence  of  copycat
     Copycat  crime  from  fictional  content  is  not  only
                                                                      crimes,  criminologists  have  long  since
     restricted  to  crime  thrillers  or  horror  genres.  The
                                                                      debated  that  crime  is  imitative.  The
     Bollywood action movie Dhoom, which showcased
                                                                      society  itself  models  the  opportunity
     theft  as  glorified  and  heroic,  inspired  the
                                                                      for      a      criminogenic         activity.
     Chelambra  Bank  Robbery  (Kerala)  on  30th
                                                                      Multimedia  development  plays  a
     December  2007.  A  four-member  gang  conducted
                                                                      major  role  in  connecting  these
     the  heist  of  80  kilograms  of  gold  and  5,000,000
                                                                      activities  to  public  perception.  The
     rupees, a net worth of 80 million Indian rupees, by
                                                                      enthusiastic  representation  of  crimes
     digging a tunnel into the bank’s floor. The group
                                                                      to  elicit  strong  responses  from  the
     even  created  several  misleads  towards  Naxalites'
                                                                      public  somewhere  gives  a  leeway  to
     activity.  After  conviction,  the  leader  of  the  gang
                                                                      imitate  such  acts.  Various  theories
     confessed to gathering inspiration from the movie
                                                                      attempt to explain the phenomenon of
     scene  where  the  movie  characters  used  the  exact
                                                                      a "copycat" or "imitative" crime.
     modus operandi of bank robbery.



                                       VERITAS VOLUME:4 ISSUE: 1]]></page><page Index="47"><![CDATA[41

      Theory of Imitation                                            Differential Association Theory
      Crime  was  associated  with  learning  and                    The  theory  of  differential  association

      observation  as  early  as  the  1890s.  French                was propounded by Edwin Sutherland

      criminologist  Gabriel  Tarde  was  the  pioneer  in           in 1939 and later modified in 1947. He
      theorizing  sociological  modelling  with  crime.  In          asserted  that  crime  is  learnt  by

      the book Le Lois de l’imtation, he proposed the                association  with  others  who  have

      three laws of imitation:                                       criminalistic  characters.  According  to
        1. Close  contact:  People  witness  and  imitate  a         him,  behavioral  learning  takes  place

          person  they  are  in  close  contact  with  or            through  personal  contact  with  other
          witness regularly.                                         people  from  family  and  peers.  This

        2. Superiority:  An  inferiority  complex  compels           learning,  in  the  context  of  crime,

          a  person  to  imitate  the  model  whom  he               encompasses  both  the  techniques  for
          regards  as  superior.  The  superiority  can  be          committing       the     crime     and     the

          either on behavior, status, or power.                      attitudes,  rationality,  or  justification
        3. Insertion:  The  imitative  behaviour  learnt             for  committing  it.  Thus,  crime

          from  the  model  replaces  the  person's                  imitation  can  be  the  effect  of  a

          individuality. The copycats ultimately adopt               person's surroundings as well.
          the behavior as their own.

      Thus,  the  psychology  of  a  copycat  criminal  is           Labelling Theory

      often  altered  to  that  of  whom  they  imitate,             Howard  Becker's  labelling  theory
      making  them  commit  acts  that  they  wouldn't               stems from the sociological perspective

      otherwise.                                                     of  symbolic  interactionism.  When

      Social Learning Theory                                         society  responds  negatively  to  a

      In  this  theory,  Albert  Bandura  argued  that  when person's  behavior  and  labels  them,  it
      an individual observes criminogenic behavior and increases  the  likelihood  of  their

      perceives  it  as  socially  desirable,  it  instills involvement  in  criminal  activities.
      "vicarious  learning."  Bandura  conducted  his Contemporary  forensic  psychologists

      famous  “Bobo  doll  experiment,”  intending  to believe that labelling can also manifest

      discover  the  impact  of  young  children  being a  concept  among  other  people,
      exposed  to  violent  behaviors.  The  study  results proliferating  the  imitation  of  such

      suggested that if people observe criminal behavior, acts.  Particularly  when  such  labels

      they  may  normalize  the  behavior.  Forensic become a symbol of fame and identity
      psychology terms this "sensationalized aggression." associated  with  the  offender.  The

      The social attention received by a particular crime glamorization  of  crime  in  media  may

      in  the  media  instigates  its  imitation.  The  crime lead to the confirmation of such acts,
      becomes an achievable and appealing goal, and the creating a copycat.

      offender is idolized.


                                       VERITAS VOLUME:4 ISSUE: 1]]></page><page Index="48"><![CDATA[42
      Contagion Theory

      In 1885, Gustave Le Bon introduced the concept
      of  "collective  behavior"  in  terms  of  social

      psychology. In his book The Crowd: A Study of

      Popular Mind in France, he stated that a person's
      individuality  can  be  moulded  towards  violence

      under the hypnotic influence of a crowd. It was
      later  reformed  by  Robert  Park  and  Herbert

      Blumer  at  different  times,  concerning  extreme             Image 3: Copycat crime cases trend (1978-2012)

      deviant  behaviors.  The  thoughts,  emotions,  and            Psychoanalysis and Surveys
      behavior of an offender can influence an entirely

      new  group  of  people,  leading  to  similar  crimes.         Ray  Surette's  model  of  unsubstantial
      Society  and  media's  detailed  focus  on  high-              and substantial copycats:

      profile  crimes  initiates  an  impulse  of  collective        In  a  2015  prison  survey  conducted  by

      behavior  in  such  silent  people  to  become                 Ray      Surette,      the      criminologist
      proactive copycat criminals.                                   discovered that out of 574 inmates, 22%


                                                                     had  committed  a  copycat  crime.
      Fad Theory
                                                                     Furthermore, they admitted to receiving
      This  theory  was  defined  by  Armando  Simon  in
                                                                     impetus  from  criminogenic  media
      the context of copycat crime after the Columbine
                                                                     coverage  or  popular  fiction.  Another
      Shooting  of  1999.  Simon  analysed  a  pattern  of
                                                                     reason  is  the  thorough  examination  of
      the  probability  of  the  copycat  phenomenon  by
                                                                     the  modus  operandi  of  crimes  for
      studying  similar  crimes  in  the  wake  of  the
                                                                     premeditation of the offence they intend
      "Columbine  Effect."  "Fad"  is  considered  to  be
                                                                     to  commit.  In  the  Indian  context,  this
      widespread enthusiasm for something, though it
                                                                     has    been     extremely      common        in
      might  be  short-lived.  According  to  Simon,  each
                                                                     homicide  cases.  One  instance  is  the
      fad qualitatively and quantitatively differs, but it
                                                                     dismembering  and  storing  of  bodies  in
      will have subsequent manifestations nonetheless.
                                                                     the fridge, which has become a massive
      Copycat  crimes  are  the  result  of  these
                                                                     media  sensation  since  the  Shraddha
      manifestations. He classified the concept of fads
                                                                     Walker  case  (2022).  However,  how
      into    two      categories:     frivolous      fads,    a
                                                                     much media content influences copycat
      manifestation  of  the  observer's  amusement  and
                                                                     criminals is still a matter of debate. On
      curiosity,  and  socio-political  fads,  involving  the
                                                                     this  basis,  imitative  crimes  have  been
      judicial  branch.  He  noted  that  copycat
                                                                     classified        as         unsubstantiated
      phenomena  such  as  the  Columbine  effect  are
                                                                     (independent  of  media  influence)  and
      mostly frivolous fads.
                                                                     Substantiated  (majorly  motivated  by

                                                                     media) crimes.



                                       VERITAS VOLUME:4 ISSUE: 1]]></page><page Index="49"><![CDATA[43

      There are 7 major factors on which the crimes are

      differentiated.



      Unsubstantiated Copycat Crime

      In  this  case,  the  imitative  phenomenon  is  not
      much  influenced  by  media.  There  is  no  direct

      crime scene specificity with any prior crimes. The

      offender      doesn’t      credit     any      particular
                                                                       Image 5: Probable influence of different fictional
      criminogenic  content  as  their  inspiration.  Thus,            genres on copycat crimes

      there is no definitive proof to conclude whether
      the  crime  was  an  intentional  copycat  or  a               Prevalence of Copycat Crime on LCFC

      coincidence in nature.                                         Concept:


      Substantiated Copycat Crime
                                                                     In  2015,  Mary  Chadee  and  Dionne
      In this case, media and criminogenic content tend
                                                                     Brewster       conducted       research      on
      to have a direct influence on crime. The offender
                                                                     copycat        motivation.        In      their
      implements several modus operandi from a single
                                                                     publication "Copycat Crime Dynamics:
      or multiple prior crimes. Repeated consumption
                                                                     The  Interplay  of  Empathy,  Narrative
      of the content and attention to specific details are
                                                                     Persuasion,  and  Risk  with  Likelihood
      present  in  their  behavior.  The  offender  might
                                                                     to     Commit       Future      Criminality,"
      even  make  a  statement  about  his  inspiration.
                                                                     Chadee and Brewster correlated media
      There  is  a  credible  connection  between  the
                                                                     with  copycat  crimes  and  estimated  the
      original crime and the copycat.
                                                                     likelihood to commit future criminality
                                                                     (LCFC).  Over  373  juveniles  from

                                                                     different educational backgrounds were
                                                                     interviewed in Trinidad, and the risk of

                                                                     copycat  crime  motivation  showed  a

                                                                     strong  positive  inclination  towards
                                                                     LCFC,       which      is    concerning      to

                                                                     criminologists.           The         research
                                                                     simultaneously  focused  on  the  role  of

                                                                     empathy  and  narrative  persuasion  in

                                                                     imitative  behavior.  Empathy  is  the
            Image 4: Surette’s seven-point classification of
                                                                     ability  to  understand  and  project  onto
            copycat crime
                                                                     the  thoughts  of  another's  emotions,  as

                                                                     well  as  imitate  and  visualize  their
                                                                     thoughts.



                                       VERITAS VOLUME:4 ISSUE: 1]]></page><page Index="50"><![CDATA[44

      The  researchers  scaled  the  feeling  of  empathy            3.Psychology  and  behavior:  mental

      using  the  Interpersonal  Reactivity  Index.  A               and     behavioral       disorders,     social

      higher sense of empathy with victims can deter                 alienation, lack of identity, personality
      crime  in  society.  Conversely,  Chadee  and                  diseases       (bipolarity,      dissociative

      Brewster debated that if the media shows more                  identity disorder), etc. can also lead to
      inclination  to  empathize  with  the  criminal,  it           the  copycat  phenomenon.  However,

      will  act  as  a  copycat  model.  In  the  same  way,         whether  copycat  criminals  have  some

      crime-persuasive  narration  can  cause  a  person             sort of psychological disorder is still a
      to  relate  to  the  crime  committer  (fictional  or          matter        of       speculation         for

      real) and imitate their behaviors. This research               criminologists.
      also  emphasized  the  need  for  cognizance                   4.Crime  aesthetic:  While  rare,  some

      (NFC). With higher NFC, copycat crimes show                    individuals  may  be  influenced  to

      a tendency to decrease.                                        imitate  a  crime  if  they  perceive  it  as
                                                                     artistic.  The  success  or  failure  of  the

      Other factors:                                                 generator       crime      fascinates      the

                                                                     imitator's  mind.  Especially  in  cases
      Further  psychoanalysis  in  recent  years  has                where  the  copycats  are  obtaining

      revealed  many  factors  influencing  the  copycat             inspiration  from  fictional  content,

      phenomenon:                                                    crime      aesthetic      is    the    major
        1. Individual  demographics:  Criteria  like  age            psychological stimulus.

          or  sex  often  influence  the  exposure  and              5.      Imitating       mindset:       Many
          consumption  of  violent  content.  Crime                  individuals, specifically those with low

          tends to provoke a greater sense of thrill in              self-esteem,  are  found  to  have  a

          youngsters than it does in mature people.                  psychology of imitating others in any
        2. Influence  of  media:  In  recent  years,  crime          form  due  to  conditioning.  Achieving

          has become a part of pop culture and a new                 rewards from such imitation increases
          fiction genre. Social media, news coverage,                this habit further, which may even be a

          books,  and  even  movies  are  glorifying                 subsequent criminal activity.

          criminogenic content. The sheer amount of                  6.Depersonalization:  A  person  can
          crime documentaries on the internet plagues                also imitate another criminal or adopt

          people's minds with ideologies of crime and                the  personality  to  reduce  their  moral

          prevention.  However,  studies  have  shown                inhibitions. This adaptation of another
          that  extreme  sensitization  to  violence  may            mindset  enables  them  to  commit  a

          create  a  sense  of  psychological  connection            violent  act  that  they  couldn’t  have

          in the viewer with the offender or fictional               committed otherwise.
          character.





                                       VERITAS VOLUME:4 ISSUE: 1]]></page><page Index="51"><![CDATA[45

      7.Risk  reduction:  In  specific  instances,  the              There  are  no  systematic  and  regular

      perpetrator  copycats  the  modus  operandi  of                studies  on  the  copycat  effect.  Even

      another criminal to mislead the criminal justice               with the 7 criteria indicators suggested
      system.  They  prioritize  concealing  their  own              by  Surette,  criminologists  find  it

      identity  behind  the  facade  of  another  well-              challenging  to  define  a  copycat
      known criminal to evade being a suspect.                       criminal.

      8.Publicity  and  glory:  Criminal  psychologists

      are also of the opinion that, just like many other             False  positive  and  false  negative  case
      crimes, copycat crimes may also be committed                   assessment        is     another       factor

      for  notoriety  and  creating  public  sensation.              hampering        the    determination       of
      Imitating infamous crimes can renew a sense of                 copycat  criminals.  Through  extensive

      fear in society, thus creating headlines.                      studies, it has been recently estimated

                                                                     that  every  1  out  of  4  offenders,  at
      Difficulties in identifying copycats                           some  point  in  their  criminal  history,

                                                                     has      attempted       copycat       crime.

      The  complex  and  multifaceted  nature  of                    However,       most      of    the    media-
      copycat crimes makes it a difficult task to link a             established  linkages  tend  to  be

      certain  case  to  the  imitation  of  another.  To            distorted or based on misinformation.

      date, the criteria to define copycat criminals are             Out  of  the  cases  reported  as  copycat
      hypothetical  and  based  on  speculation.  The                crimes  by  media  in  the  past  four

      gauge  for  determining  the  nature  of  crime                decades,  only  around  40%  of  the
      imitation  is  based  on  the  analysis  of  a  very           assessment is based on what is believed

      limited  number  of  cases.  There  is  no  tested             to be adequate information. In almost

      credibility  as  to  the  existence  of  the  “copycat”        a  quarter  of  the  declared  copycat
      phenomenon.  Furthermore,  this  concept  was                  crimes,  the  claims  are  not  based  on

      initially theorized by the media and not so much               any direct evidence. This has relatively
      by criminologists.                                             increased  the  trend  of  false  positive

      Another  major  issue  with  identifying  copycat              copycat crime analysis.

      crimes is that, unlike other categories of crime,
      these  imitative  offences  are  not  properly

      draughted  and  tallied  with  the  original  crime.

      The  extent  of  the  imitations  is  also  not
      statistically  compared.  Innumerable  copycat

      crimes  go  unrecorded  between  the  original

      crime  and  the  media-insighted  ones  due  to  a
      lack of documentation.





                                       VERITAS VOLUME:4 ISSUE: 1]]></page><page Index="52"><![CDATA[46


      CONCLUSION                                                     REFERENCES



      Despite having conducted extensive research,                        David Dressler. Case of the

      identifying  and  preventing  the  copycat                          Copycat Criminal; When
      phenomenon remains a daunting task for the                          crime comes in waves, simple

      criminal  justice  system.  One  of  the  main                      imitation plays a large part in
      challenges is the media itself propagating the                      the phenomenon. A veteran

      concept of copycat crime while also being an                        observer explains why this

      influence  behind  it.  Prevention  of  over-                       should be so. Copycat
      glorification  of  criminogenic  contents  and                      Criminal. The New York

      sensationalization of the offender can help to                      Times (Dec10, 1961).

      reduce  these  crimes.  It  is  also  necessary  to                 https://www.nytimes.com/196
      have more knowledge and studies on copycat                          1/12/10/archives/case-of-the-

      trends,  along  with  an  understanding  of                         copycat-criminal-when-

      criminal psychology, to eradicate the scope of                      crime-comes-in-waves-
      crimes in the future.                                               simple.html

      Researchers  believe  that  if  the  catalysts  and
      triggers  of  copycat  phenomena  can  be                               Clark, J., & Dove, L. L.

      identified,  there  would  be  a  significant                       (2024, June 7). 10 notable

      decrease  in  the  number  of  imitative  crimes.                   copycat killers.
      Studies  showed  that  certain  populations  of                     HowStuffWorks.

      society are more susceptible to these triggers,                     https://people.howstuffworks
      such      as     adolescents,      men,      extreme                .com/5-copycat-killers.htm

      criminogenic  content  consumers,  people

      exposed to violence and gore, etc. However,                         Tnn. (2017, October 26).
      the triggers are still undetermined due to the                      Dhoom-inspired gang found

      lack of further in-depth research. Currently,                       guilty. The Times of India.

      restriction  on  specific  media  contents  is  the                 https://timesofindia.indiatime
      most  logical  approach  against  copycat                           s.com/city/kozhikode/dhoom

      crimes.                                                             -inspired-gang-found-

                                                                          guilty/articleshow/19119372.c

                                                                          ms














                                       VERITAS VOLUME:4 ISSUE: 1]]></page><page Index="53"><![CDATA[47




                   Simon, A. (2007).Application                      Chadee, D., Surette, R.,

                   of  FAD theory to copycat                         Chadee, M., & Brewster, D.

                   crime.Quantitative data                           (2017). Copycat crime
                   following the Coloumbian                          dynamics: The interplay of

                   massacre. Psychological                           empathy, narrative
                   Reports, 100(3), 1233.                            persuasion and risk with

                   https://doi.org/10.2466/pr0.1                     likelihood to commit future

                   00.3.1233-1244                                    criminality. Psychology of
                                                                     Popular Media Culture, 6(2),

                   LiCausi, Jamie, "Copycat                          142–158.

                   Crime" (2017).                                    https://doi.org/10.1037/ppm0
                   Undergraduate Honors                              000088

                   College Theses 2016-. 33.

                   https://digitalcommons.liu.ed                     Research, I. J. O. L. a. L.
                   u/post_honors_theses/33                           (2021, December 3). Copycat
                                                                     crimes: an increasing trend?

                   Surette, R. (2016).                               IJLLR.

                   Measuring copycat crime.                          https://www.ijllr.com/post/co

                   Crime, Media, Culture,                            pycat-crimes-an-increasing-
                   12(1), 37-64.                                     trend

                   https://doi.org/10.1177/17416
                   59015601172                                       Psychologs Magazine. (2023,
                                                                     December 14). The


                   Surette, R. (2015). Thought                       psychology behind copycat
                   bite: A case study of the                         crimes. Psychology Magazine

                   social construction of a crime                    | Mental Health Magazine |

                   and justice concept. Crime                        Psychology Magazine | Self-
                   Media Culture an                                  Help Magazine.

                   International Journal, 11(2),                     https://www.psychologs.com/

                   105–135.                                          the-psychology-behind-copy-
                   https://doi.org/10.1177/17416                     cat-crimes/

                   59015588401












                                       VERITAS VOLUME:4 ISSUE: 1]]></page><page Index="54"><![CDATA[Infographics | by Anashwara Pramod & Keziah Angel                                                              48]]></page><page Index="55"><![CDATA[A









         S










        E



































                 S T U D I E S]]></page><page Index="56"><![CDATA[50
                                               "SHREYA SINGHAL VS
          AUTHOR: PRIYANKA
                                               UNION OF INDIA: A
                  GHOSH
                                               TURNING POINT FOR

                                               INTERNET FREEDOM"





                                                 INTRODUCTION
      DID YOU

      KNOW ??                                    The Supreme Court’s ruling in Shreya Singhal v. The


                                                 Union of India in 2015 marked a significant turning
         Net neutrality is a principle
                                                 point for digital rights and freedom of speech in India.
            that requires internet
                                                 The court invalidated Section 66A of the Information
         service providers (ISPs) to
           treat all internet traffic            Technology Act, which had deemed "offensive" online
          equally, regardless of the             speech as criminal, declaring it unconstitutional. This
           content, application, or              pivotal decision ensured the protection of citizens'

                    device.                      rights to free expression online and established a
                                                 precedent for future legal disputes regarding overly

                                                 broad and ambiguous restrictions on digital discourse.
       Significance


                                                  This decision created a legal standard for future issues
       The case of Shreya Singhal v.              involving  digital  rights,  highlighting  the  judiciary's
       The  Union  of  India  (2015)  is          role in defending fundamental liberties.

       notable because it invalidated
       Section       66A        of      the       Furthermore, it encouraged a livelier public discourse

       Information  Technology  Act,              on digital platforms and empowered citizens to speak

       which  had  been  used  to                 their  thoughts  without  the  fear  of  unjustified  legal
       arbitrarily  restrict  free  speech        consequences,         thereby       affecting       worldwide

       online.  The  Supreme  Court's             conversations       regarding      the    balance      between
       decision  was  a  watershed                regulation  and  freedom  of  expression  in  the  digital

       moment  for  digital  rights,              era.

       protecting people's freedom of
       expression on the internet and

       limiting the potential abuse of

       unclear  and  broad  legislative
       provisions to stifle dissent and

       political commentary.





                                       VERITAS VOLUME:4 ISSUE: 1]]></page><page Index="57"><![CDATA[51


     BACKGROUND                                                      In  this  case,  they  argued  that  the

                                                                     provision  of  excessive  combination  is
     Section  66A:  Section  66A  of  the  Information               too broad and can prevent free speech

     Technology Act, 2000 (IT Act) criminalizes the                  or arbitrary enforcement.
     sending  of  offensive  messages  through  a

     computer or other communication device. It was                  Arguments        Contention       By      the

     introduced  by  the  Information  Technology                    Petitioner (Shreya Singhal):
     (Amendment)  Act  of  2008  to  protect  women

     from  cybercrime  like  vulgar  mobile  phone                   1.Violation  of  Free  Expression  and
     messages.                                                       Speech:  By  way  of  violation,  Section

                                                                     66A infringed upon Article 19(1)(a) of

     This retaliatory provision was later called out as              the Indian Constitution as its "chilling
     an  overly  broad  and  vague  measure  against                 effect"    brought      about      arbitrary

     providing  insulting  or  deceptive  information                imperatives on free speech.

     through  electronic  media,  thus  opening  doors
     for  the  power  to  abuse  by  organs  of  the  state.         2.Overbroad  and  vague:  The  terms

     The spate of arrests for comments online, often                 were  excessively  ambiguous  (words

     by  political  elites  or  expressing  other  opinions,         such     as    "grossly     offensive"     or
     was  the  catalyst  behind  a  legal  challenge.  In  a         'menacing  character'),  leading  to

     case  that  hit  the  headlines  in  2012,  two  young          unpredictable, arbitrary application.
     women  named  Shaheen  Dhada  and  Rinu

     Shrinivasan  were  arrested  for  expressing  their             3.Mere  Restrictions:  The  restrictions

     opinion  on  Facebook  against  the  Mumbai                     were  far  more  than  necessary  or
     Bandh, which was declared by Shiv Sena due to                   reasonable;  Article  19(2)  could  never

     the death of the leader named Bal Thackrey in                   have  allowed  something  like  this,
     Mumbai.  These  arrests  generated  immense                     where  a  huge  chunk  of  expression

     public outrage all over, which seemed to confirm                across     the     spectrum       is   being

     fears  that  Section  66A  could  easily  be  misused           criminalised.
     for harassment and suppression.

                                                                     4. A lot of significant arrests that have

     On the back of this, law student Shreya Singhal                 been made in the name of UAPA are
     filed  public  interest  litigation  (PIL)  before  the         arbitrary  and  misused.  The  law  is

     Supreme Court, objecting that Section 66A was                   undeniably targeted at dissent; anyone

     not neutral and in dissonance with Article 19(1)                engaged in some political criticism has
     (a),  guaranteeing  free  speech  and  expression               faced  jail,  including  comments  on

     under constitutional rights.                                    social media.




                                       VERITAS VOLUME:4 ISSUE: 1]]></page><page Index="58"><![CDATA[52


      Arguments put forth by the respondent (The union               It  upheld  Section  69A  and  the
      of India):                                                     Information  Technology  (Procedure

                                                                     and  Safeguards  for  Blocking  Access

      1.Regulation Necessity: Section 66A was needed                 to  Information  by  the  Public)  Rules
      to     prevent      the     misuse      of     electronic      2009.  Section  79  was  declared

      communication for dangerous activities such as                 constitutionally  valid,  but  subject  to
      issuing threats and defamation among people.                   Section  79(3)(b)  being  read  down.

                                                                     The        Information         Technology

      2.Reasonable  restrictions:  The  provision  that              "Intermediary  Guidelines"  Rules  of
      sought  to  protect  decency  and  morality  among             2011  were  also  held  valid.  Section

      the  people  would  be  construed  as  a  reasonable           118(d)  of  the  Kerala  Police  Act  was

      restriction  under  Article  19(2)  on  freedom  of            deemed unconstitutional.
      speech.


                                                                     REFERENCES
      3.Public  purpose:  The  law  was  serving  a
      legitimate  public  cause  by  protecting  people
                                                                          Nariman, R. (2015). Shreya
      from harmful and objectionable content on the
                                                                          Singhal vs U.O.I on 24
      internet.
                                                                          March 2015. IN THE

                                                                          SUPREME COURT OF
      4. Safeguards and recommendations: Instead of
                                                                          INDIA.
      declaring  the  whole  clause  impossible  to
                                                                          http://indiankanoon.org/doc
      implement,  safeguards  were  recommended  as
                                                                          /110813550/
      well.


                                                                           Lalit, U. U., Rastogi, A., &
      Judgement:
                                                                          Bhat, S. R. (2022).

                                                                          ORDER. IN THE
      The  Supreme  Court  discussed  freedom  of
                                                                          SUPREME COURT OF
      expression,  focussing  on  three  fundamental
                                                                          INDIA.
      concepts: discussion, advocacy, and incitement.

      The  court  struck  down  Section  66A  of  the

      Information  Technology  Act,  2000,  stating  it
      violated  Article  19(1)(a)  and  was  not  saved

      under Article 19(2).












                                       VERITAS VOLUME:4 ISSUE: 1]]></page><page Index="59"><![CDATA[53


        AUTHOR: ANSILMARY                   MURDER OF LYON SISTERS





                                            INTRODUCTION



                                            Sheila Mary Lyon, who was born on March 30, 1962, and
      DID YOU
                                            Katherine Mary Lyon, who was born on March 29, 1964,
      KNOW ??                               are  two  of  the  four  children  born  to  their  parents,  John

                                            and Mary Lyon. They were residing on Plyers Mill Road.
       Police dogs, also called K9
                                            On March 25, 1975, the two girls went missing. They were
          sniffers, can search a
        crime scene area 4 times            last seen inside the Orange Bowl restaurant talking to an
         faster than any human.             unidentified man. Sheila and Katherine were 12 and 10 at

        They have 10,000 times              the time of the disappearance.
        stronger olfactory sense,
          making them the best

           evidence detectors
                                                                                  Lots of flyers and posters
                                                                                  were  published,  but  they
       Disappearance
                                                                                  were in vain due to a lack
                                                                                  of evidence.
       On March 25, 1975, the two

       girls went to Wheaton Plaza
                                                                                  Reopening of the case
       shopping  centre,  which  is            Image 1: Sheila Lyon and Katherine

       about half a mile from their            Lyon
                                                                                  For  decades,  the  case
       home.  When  the  girls  did
                                               The  police  investigation         remained  unsolved,  but
       not return by dinner time, a
                                               started with the search for        between  2012  and  2013,
       search was conducted. They
                                               the  girls.  They  did  a          the  Montgomery  County
       were  last  seen  inside  the
                                               thorough  search  through          Police  decided  to  reopen
       Orange      Bowl      restaurant
                                               the entire town, inspecting        the     case.    Instead      of
       talking to an unknown man
                                               every  house,  shop,  and          treating  the  case  like  a
       with  a  tape  recorder,  but  a
                                               place. Dogs were brought           cold case, they decided to
       few  days  later,  a  man
                                               so they could pick up the          reinvestigate it as an open
       claimed  that  he  saw  an
                                               scent,  and  they  did  pick       case         using         new
       unidentified      man      in    a
                                               up the scent and followed          technological methods.
       moving  automobile  with
                                               the  trail  where  the  two
       two girls behind him bound
                                               girls  had  likely  taken  it,
       and gagged.
                                               but the trail had ended up
                                               in the parking lot.


                                       VERITAS VOLUME:4 ISSUE: 1]]></page><page Index="60"><![CDATA[54

















                                                                             Image 4: Sketch of the
                                                                             unidentified suspect

                                                             Investigation



                                                             The police decided to rule Welch as a prime

                                                             suspect.  In  2015,  when  the  police  were
               Image 2: Toledo Blade press report            interrogating  Welch,  he  finally  admitted

                                                             that he left the Wheaton Plaza with the two
                                                             girls but denied killing them. But he blamed
        During the investigation, with possible
                                                             his  uncle,  Richard  Welch,  for  murdering
        pieces of evidence, the police were able
                                                             the  girls.  At  that  time,  Welch  was  already
        to  retrieve  a  mugshot  taken  in  the
                                                             serving a sentence for assaulting a minor in
        1970s of Lloyd Welch Jr., and it had a
                                                             South  Carolina.  Unable  to  find  proper
        striking  resemblance  to  the  sketch  of
                                                             evidence, Virginia police decided to search
        the  unidentified  suspect  that  was
                                                             for Welch’s property.
        responsible  for  the  Lyon  sisters'

        abduction.
                                                             During  the  confession,  he  told  the  police
                                                             gruesome things that were done to the Lyon

                                                             sisters, but claimed that it was someone else
                                                             who  had  done  it.  He  said  that  he  saw  his

                                                             father  and  his  uncle  dismember  the  girls

                                                             and  put  them  in  a  duffle  bag,  which  was
                                                             taken out to be burned. In December 2014,

                                                             Henry Parker, who is the cousin of Welch,
                                                             confessed to the police that back in 1975, he


                  Image 3: Mugshot of                        helped  Welch  take  out  a  duffle  bag  that
                  Llyod Welch Jr.                            smelt like blood and had stains all over it,
                                                             and they threw the bag in a fire in a remote

                                                             area in Bedford County, Virginia.








                                       VERITAS VOLUME:4 ISSUE: 1]]></page><page Index="61"><![CDATA[55


      Aftermath                                                      REFERENCES



      After  42  years  of  the  unsolved  case,  on                      Case File of Katherine and

      September 12, 2017, Welch finally pleaded guilty                    Sheila Lyon. (n.d.).
      to  the  murder  of  the  Lyon  sisters.  He  was                   https://www.forthelost.org/l

      sentenced  to  48  years  in  prison.  Many  people                 yon.html
      and  experts  have  questions  about  the  case

      because of its cloudiness, but justice was served                   Lavelle, M. (2024, May 8).

      to the Lyon sisters.                                                How investigators solved

                                                                          the gruesome Lyon Sisters

                                                                          mystery after unearthing a
                                                                          40-year-old sketch. Ranker.

                                                                          https://www.ranker.com/list/

                                                                          facts-about-lyon-
                                                                          case/matthew-lavelle



                                                                          29, 1975. (1975, March 29).

                                                                          Newspapers.com.

                                                                          https://www.newspapers.co
               Image 5: Lloyd Welch in the courtroom
               during the sentencing for murdering the                    m/article/the-news-29-
               Lyon sisters.                                              1975/135386886/











































                                       VERITAS VOLUME:4 ISSUE: 1]]></page><page Index="62"><![CDATA[56
                AUTHOR:                     KOODATHAI CYANIDE

     SENATRA NAINA SILVERIA                 KILLINGS

          SREEVIDYA REJITH


                                            INTRODUCTION



                                            It  was  a  series  of  unnatural  deaths  later  on  regarded  as

      DID YOU                               murders….
                                            In 2019, police arrested a woman named Jolly Joseph, a
      KNOW ??                               resident  of  Koodathai  in  Kozhikode  district  of  Kerala.

      Cyanide, though colorless,            The  murders  took  place  over  a  period  of  14  years  (2002
       has a bitter almond odor.
                                            -2016). Each time Jolly had managed to dodge suspicion,
      Thus, in most cases, poison
                                            until  her  brother-in-law  and  sister-in-law  got  suspicion
        is administered via food
          and drink to make it              and decided to have the deaths in the family investigated.
              undetectable








        Jolly  was  originally  from
        Kattappana,             Idukki

        district in Kerala. Her first

        marriage  was  in  1997  i.e.
        Roy  Thomas,  they  had                                     Image 1: Jolly and her family

        two  sons.  Despite  having
        only      a      plus      two         Timeline of crimes

        qualification, she managed

        to    masquerade        as    a        2002:  Annamma  Thomas 2008: Tom Thomas aged
        professor        at       NIT,         aged  57,  mother-in-law  of 66,  father-in-law  of  the

        Kozhikode,        successfully         the accused, drank a glass of accused,  passed  away
        deceiving       the       local        water  after  returning  home after  fainting  inside  the

        community.  In  2011,  her             from        a      walk       and bathroom  and  when  he

        husband  Roy  Thomas                   immediately  felt  uneasy  and was           rushed      to     the
        died  mysteriously.  Later,            eventually  collapsed  on  the hospital,  they  declared

        in 2016, she got married to            floor.  She  was  taken  to  the that  it  was  due  to  heart

        Shaju Zachariah.                       hospital where she died later attack.
                                               on, the doctors declared that No             postmortem        was
                                               the  death  was  due  to  heart conducted  on  either  of

                                               attack.                              their bodies.


                                       VERITAS VOLUME:4 ISSUE: 1]]></page><page Index="63"><![CDATA[57


                                                                  Time when everything changed



                                                                  Immediately after Jolly's father-in-law’s

                                                                  death,  she  produced  an  unsigned  will
                                                                  where he had given most of the property

                                                                  to  Roy  and  Jolly.  Roy's  siblings
                                                                  disbelieved it, therefore….




                                                                  2018:  Rojo  Thomas,  brother  of  Roy
                                                                  filed  a  series  of  RTI  applications,  and

                                                                  received a copy of the autopsy report of
                 Image 2: Timeline of the crime
                                                                  his brother's body from the government
                                                                  hospital.

      2011:  Roy  Thomas  aged  40,  Jolly’s  first

      husband.  He  died  by  collapsing  in  the                 Rojo found out that Jolly had lied about

      bathroom  in  a  similar  manner  like  his                 Roy not having food after 3:30pm. But
      parents.  A  postmortem  was  done  and  it                 it  was  clearly  mentioned  in  the  report

      revealed  the  traces  of  cyanide  in  his  body,          that he had rice and Bengal gram curry
      but  it  was  not  further  investigated  and  the          at 8:30pm.

      case was closed calling it a death by suicide

      due to financial issues.                                    Dr.  V.  V.  Pillay,  head  of  Forensic
                                                                  Medicine  &  Toxicology  explained  that

      2014:  Mathew  being  the  maternal  uncle  of              acute  cyanide  poisoning  can  result  in

      Roy  was  the  next  victim.  She  killed  him  to          death  in  a  matter  of  seconds.  Cyanide
      cover up the 3 murders committed earlier. He                does not accumulate in the body and so

      was given poisoned whisky which caused the                  it  is  rare  to  encounter  it  in  slow  death

      death.  In  the  same  year  Shaju’s  two  old              cases.
      daughter,  Alphine  died  due  to  choking  on

      food.                                                       Rojo  submitted  a  petition  to  the
                                                                  Vadakara police and later the bodies of

      2016: Sily Shaju aged 41, Alphine’s mother,                 all  the  six  deceased  were  exhumed  and

      was  given  a  mushroom  capsule  by  Jolly,                examined  in  detail,  revealing  that  they
      which she convinced Sily that it would help                 died due to murder.

      her with the depression she had and she died
      on the spot after consuming it.







                                       VERITAS VOLUME:4 ISSUE: 1]]></page><page Index="64"><![CDATA[58


        Other suspects involved                                 REFERENCES
                                                                     Staff, O. (2019, October 8).

        Mathew.  M.  S:  -  He  was  a  Jewellery                    Koodathayi cyanide murders: The

        shop  employee  who  was  a  distant                         story so far. OnManorama.
        relative of Jolly. He provided Jolly the                     https://web.archive.org/web/20191016

        cyanide  that  he  obtained  from  Praji                     000701/https:/english.manoramaonlin
        Kumar  after  giving  him  alcohol  and                      e.com/news/kerala/2019/10/08/koodat

        money.  He  said  that  she  asked  him                      hayi-morders-story-so-far.html

        cyanide to kill a stray dog. He was also
        the lover of Jolly.                                          Cherian, D. (2019, October 9). Kerala

        Praji  Kumar:  -  He  was  the  goldsmith                    serial killer Jolly: Everything you

        who  gave  M.S.  Mathew  the  cyanide,                       need to know. India – Gulf News.
        where he assumed that the poison was                         https://web.archive.org/web/20191016

        bought to kill rats.                                         075502/https:/gulfnews.com/world/asi

                                                                     a/india/kerala-serial-killer-jolly-
        Motive                                                       everything-you-need-to-know-

                                                                     1.1570526945036
        The investigators discovered that Jolly

        Joseph  had  forged  documents  to                           Wikipedia contributors. (2024, July

        acquire the properties of the deceased.                      16). Koodathayi cyanide killings.
                                                                     Wikipedia.

        CONCLUSION                                                   https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Koodat
                                                                     hayi_cyanide_killings

        In  October  2019,  the  police  arrested

        Jolly, M.S. Mathew and Praji Kumar.                           Philip, S. (2019, October 10). Using
        The  case  was  in  trial  stage  at  the                    cyanide, Kerala woman murdered six

        Kozhikode  Additional  Session  court,                       members of family over 14 years, say

        Jolly  argued  that  she  had  been  an                      police. The Indian Express.
        accused  without  sufficient  evidence                       https://web.archive.org/web/20231224

        against  her.  She  filed  a  petition  in  the              155541/https:/indianexpress.com/artic

        court  but  it  got  discharged.  She                        le/india/kerala/using-cyanide-kerala-
        approached the Kerala High Court but                         woman-murdered-six-members-of-

        in  2023  her  plea  was  dismissed  saying                  family-over-14-years-say-police-
        that  there  was  enough  evidence                           6055693/

        connecting  her  to  her  first  husband’s

        murder, and the trial still goes on…




                                       VERITAS VOLUME:4 ISSUE: 1]]></page><page Index="65"><![CDATA[59
                                            GLORIA RAMIREZ – THE
                 AUTHOR:


          ROTHIKA GANAPATHI                 ‘TOXIC LADY’



                                             INTRODUCTION



                                             On  the  evening  of  February  19,  1994,  around  8:15  PM,

      DID YOU                                Gloria Ramirez was brought to the emergency department
                                             by  paramedics  at  the  Riverside  General  Hospital  in
       KNOW ??
                                             Riverside,  California.  She  was  confused,  suffering  from
                                             heart  palpitations  (Tachycardia)  and  Cheyne-Stokes
           Researchers of mass
      hysteria note that episodes            respiration.

        frequently involve young
                                             The  staff  also  noticed  an  oily  sheen  covering  her  body.
      women and many recorded
                                             Before  Nurse  Kane  passed  out,  she  gave  the  tube  to  a
         cases have occurred in
          convents or schools.               medical  resident,  Julie  Gorchynski,  who  noticed  manila-
                                             coloured crystals flowing along with the bloodstream. This

                                             was  noted  by  the  attending  physician,  Dr.  Humberto

                                             Ochoa. Dr Julie stated she felt lightheaded and sat on the
       She  had  been  earlier
                                             nurse’s  desk.  Before  she  could  respond  to  the  staff’s
       diagnosed with metastatic
                                             question,  she  passed  out.  Respiratory  therapist  Dr.
       cervical  cancer.  Hospital
                                             Maureen Welch was the third to faint. Upon this reaction,
       staff           administered
                                             the ER Department was evacuated, and the skeleton crew
       midazolam,         lorazepam
                                             continued  to  stabilize  Ramirez.  The  hospital  declared  an
       and  diazepam  to  sedate
                                             internal  emergency.  After  45  minutes  of  CPR  (Cardio-
       Ramirez.  Approximately
                                             Pulmonary Resuscitation) and defibrillation, Ramirez was
       15 minutes later, Ramirez
                                             pronounced  dead  from  kidney  failure  due  to  her  cancer.
       went  into  full  cardiac
                                             Around 23 out of 37 ER staff were affected. Around 11 pm,
       arrest.  As  a  routine  of
                                             the hazard team came into the hospital with hazmat suits to
       CODE        BLUE,       Nurse
                                             check for hazardous chemicals, but couldn’t find any.
       Susan  Kane  drew  blood
       for  arterial  blood  gas
                                             Two  days  later,  Ramirez’s  body  was  taken  to  Riverside’s
       determination; she noticed
                                             coroner's  office  for  post-mortem  examination.  They
       a  foul  odor  and  passed
                                             collected  samples  of  tissue  and  blood,  as  well  as  air  from
       out  while  the  other  staff
                                             the  body  bed,  but  they  were  unable  to  draw  any  firm
       were  trying  to  defibrillate
                                             conclusions. Her death was deemed by county officials as
       her heart.
                                             "the  most  baffling  in  local  history,"  and  the  mystery

                                             sparked a media frenzy.


                                       VERITAS VOLUME:4 ISSUE: 1]]></page><page Index="66"><![CDATA[60


      In  the  end,  the  case  was  looked  at  by              The  "fruity,  garlicky  smell"  could  have
      medical  detectives  from  10  different                   been  the  "environmental  trigger"  for  this

      municipal,  state,  and  federal  forensic                 episode  of  mass  hysteria.  However,
      departments.  The  case  officially  ended                 Maureen  Welch  and  Julie  Gorchynski

      once  it  was  determined  that  Gloria's                  believed they had not been victims of mass

      cervical cancer-related renal failure was the              hysteria, and Gorchynski even launched a
      official  cause  of  death,  namely  cardiac               lawsuit, claiming that her injuries were not

      dysrhythmia.  The  cause  of  the  rash  of                caused by it.
      illnesses in the ER was still unknown, but

      mass  hysteria  was  declared  by  the                     The emergency room illnesses were caused

      coroner's office. Julie Gorchynski launched                by  an  excess  of  DMSO2.  The  Livermore
      a  $6  million  lawsuit  against  the  coroner's           Laboratory first proposed this theory. The

      office  in  the  hospital  for  claiming  mass             Laboratory  identified  unusually  high

      hysteria.  She  stated,  among  other  things,             levels of the chemical DMSO2 in Gloria's
      that her avascular necrosis was not caused                 postmortem  samples.  The  scent  of  garlic

      by    public     hysteria.     Other      hospital         and  oily  sheen  could  be  attributed  to  the

      employees also filed complaints. However,                  cancer gel.
      Gorchynski's  case  appears  to  have  been

      dropped.  It  is  unclear  what  happened  to              DMSO,  which  is  cited  in  the  scientific
      the  others.  She  was  dubbed  ‘The  Toxic                literature,  is  a  chemical  warfare  agent

      Lady’ by the media.                                        created  by  unusual  concurrence  of

                                                                 chemical reactions.
      Theories

                                                                 DMSO  is  converted  to  DMSO2,  which
          Mass  hysteria  was  the  source  of                   was discovered in her system, most likely

          emergency        room       ailments.     The          as  a  result  of  paramedics  administering

          California  Department  of  Health  and                oxygen.
          Human  Services  conducted  interviews

          with     34     emergency       room      staff        Ramirez's      sudden       drop     in     blood

          members  to  develop  this  notion.  The               temperature in the emergency room could
          Department  stated  that  there  was  no               have created DMSO4, a lethal compound,

          poison in Gloria's system and that no                  but her body temperature was too high.

          one  in  the  ambulance  on  its  route  to
          the hospital had any symptoms.








                                       VERITAS VOLUME:4 ISSUE: 1]]></page><page Index="67"><![CDATA[61



          Emergency  defibrillation  electric  shocks  may
          have converted DMSO2 into DMSO4, causing

          symptoms in emergency room staff. Livermore
          scientists suggest the temperature change from

          98.6 °F (37 °C) to 64 °F (18 °C) may have also

          contributed to this conversion.



          Ramirez's  body  was  released  for  autopsy  and
          burial  in  Olivewood  Memorial  Park,  with

          Livermore's       DMSO         conclusion      claiming

          hospital  staff  symptoms,  while  her  family
          disagreed.






             REFERENCES



                  Wiki, C. T. B. U. (n.d.). The Bizarre Toxic
                  Death Of Gloria Ramirez. BuzzFeed

                  Unsolved Wiki. https://buzzfeed-

                  unsolved.fandom.com/wiki/The_Bizarre_Toxi
                  c_Death Of_Gloria_Ramirez



                  Grant, P. M., Haas, J. S., Whipple, R. E., &

                  Andresen, B. D. (1997). A possible chemical

                  explanation for the events associated with the
                  death of Gloria Ramirez at Riverside General

                  Hospital. Forensic Science International,

                  87(3), 219–237. https://doi.org/10.1016/s0379-
                  0738(97)00076-5




                  Death of Gloria Ramirez. (2024, July 18).
                  Wikipedia.

                  https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Death_of_Gloria
                  Ramirez










                                       VERITAS VOLUME:4 ISSUE: 1]]></page><page Index="68"><![CDATA[62

                 AUTHOR:                    INSULIN: A VITAL FRIEND,

          ZEEL PANDYA AND                   A HIDDEN FOE


       ASHWITHA KATHIRESAN
                                            INTRODUCTION



                                            On the morning of 4 May 1957, just after 2 am, Dr. David
                                            Price,  a  forensic  pathologist,  was  called  to  the  home  of
        DID YOU                             Elizabeth  and  Kenneth  Barlow  in  a  residential  suburb  of

        KNOW ??                             Bradford,  Yorkshire.  The  story  was  that  Kenneth  Barlow

                                            had  discovered  his  wife  unconscious  in  the  bath  at  about
       Insulin toxicity, unlike most
        other poisons, cannot be            11.20  pm  the  previous  night  and  called  his  doctor,  who
        detected through autopsy            diagnosed her as dead.

       due to lack of validated test.
       Additional toxicological and
                                             She decided to take a bath, and Kenneth lay on the bed and
          histological analysis is
                  needed.                    went  to  sleep  at  about  9.45  pm  to  the  sound  of  the  bath
                                             running. When he woke up at around 11.20 pm, Elizabeth

                                             had not returned to bed. When he went into the bathroom,
       Kenneth,  a  38-year-old
                                             he found her submerged beneath the water. He tried to lift
       state-registered nurse, was
                                             her  out  but  did  not  have  the  strength  to  do  so.  He  tried
       unemployed.         He     had
                                             holding her head above until all the water had run out of
       married       Elizabeth      11
                                             the tub. And then he tried artificial respiration by ‘pressing
       months earlier and was, to
                                             on her abdomen’ as he was unable to lift her from the bath.
       all  outward  appearances,
                                             After  this  was  unsuccessful,  he  ran  next  door  to  his
       living  happily  with  her
                                             neighbours  and  asked  them  to  call  a  doctor,  who  in  turn
       and his 10-year-old son by
                                             called the police.
       his first wife.

                                             Dr. Price, the home forensic pathologist who was called by
       According  to  Kenneth,
                                             the  police,  conducted  a  post-mortem  examination  and
       she was tired and went to
                                             found out that Elizabeth died from drowning and was two
       bed.  When  Kenneth  went
                                             months pregnant. Blood and urine samples were thereafter
       to  bed  at  about  9.30  pm,
                                             taken  for  analysis  to  the  North-Eastern  Forensic  Science
       he  found  that  Elizabeth
                                             Laboratory, which did not identify any traces of common
       had vomited on the bed.
                                             poisons.  However,  Dr.  Price  and  the  police  believed  that

                                             Elizabeth had been unconscious when her death occurred.








                                       VERITAS VOLUME:4 ISSUE: 1]]></page><page Index="69"><![CDATA[63
                                                                Later, a more sensitive and precise method
      Four  days  later,  Elizabeth’s  body  was  re-
                                                                of  measuring  insulin  in  body  fluids  was
      examined  thoroughly  and  under  bright
                                                                available. With the new technique, Dr Peter
      light,  and  two  hypodermic  injection  sites
                                                                Wright  of  Guy's  Hospital  in  London
      were identified in each buttock. This was a
                                                                supported Dr Gurd's findings, hence giving
      breakthrough, as Dr. Price stored them in a
                                                                concrete proof of evidence against Kenneth
      refrigerator until he could find the scientist
                                                                Barlow.
      with  the  expertise  and  facilities  to  take  an

      insulin test.
                                                                Forensic experts discovered two hypodermic

                                                                injection  sites  on  the  buttocks  during  the
      Dr.  MR  Gurd  of  the  research  laboratories
                                                                investigation  of  Elizabeth  Barlow's  death,
      of the Boots drug company, which was one
                                                                which  gave  rise  to  suspicion  that  she  had
      of three British manufacturers of insulin at
                                                                been  injected  with  insulin.  Initial  tests
      the time, undertook to perform the test. Dr.
                                                                revealed the presence of insulin, a substance
      Gurd  did  not  hold  out  much  hope  of
                                                                for  which  Elizabeth  had  no  medical  need.
      success,  as  he  thought  the  technique  might
                                                                Kenneth  Barlow  confessed  to  having
      not be sensitive enough to detect the small
                                                                injected  her  but  maintained  it  was
      amount  of  insulin  that  would  be  found  in
                                                                ergometrine,  not  insulin,  and  persisted  it
      the tissues of someone who had received an
                                                                was  with  her  permission  and  collaboration
      insulin  injection.  However,  Dr.  Gurd  did
                                                                to    carry     out     an     illegal   abortion.
      find  easily  measurable  quantities  of  insulin
                                                                Toxicological tests, however, ruled out any
      in  extracts  of  the  tissues  taken  from
                                                                such       possibility      after      subsequent
      Elizabeth's  buttocks.  For  comparison,  Dr.
                                                                examination  of  needles  and  syringes  found
      Price  had  removed  tissues  from  other
                                                                in the kitchen.
      corpses, which Dr. Gurd treated in the same

      way.  As  he  expected,  he  found  no  trace  of
                                                                Further     tests    by     advanced      methods
      insulin in them. The findings from Elizabeth
                                                                confirmed  the  insulin,  which  was  broken
      were  thus  clearly  abnormal  and  therefore
                                                                down after the injection. There seemed to be
      highly suspicious.
                                                                no motive, but evidence pointed to Kenneth

                                                                administering  insulin  to  render  Elizabeth
      On  5  July,  two  months  after  Elizabeth's
                                                                unconscious  and  then  drowning  her  in  the
      death, Dr. Gurd reported that he had been
                                                                bath.  Despite  his  determination,  the
      able to recover from three separate samples
                                                                evidence—coupled  with  his  earlier  remarks
      of Elizabeth's buttocks, a total of about 84
                                                                about  the  lethal  effects  of  insulin—ensured
      units of insulin, enough to keep two insulin-
                                                                his conviction for murder in 1957.
      dependent  diabetic  patients  going  for  a

      whole day. Elizabeth did not have diabetes,

      nor had she been prescribed insulin.


                                       VERITAS VOLUME:4 ISSUE: 1]]></page><page Index="70"><![CDATA[64




       Kenneth  was  jailed  for  life  but  still
       protested his innocence up until his release

       in 1984. The case has been cited as the first

       case of murder by insulin.





             REFERENCES



                  Marks, V., & Richmond, C. (2008).

                  Kenneth Barlow: The first
                  documented case of murder by

                  insulin. Journal of the Royal Society

                  of Medicine, 101(1), 19–21.
                  https://doi.org/10.1258/jrsm.2007.071

                  002


























































                                       VERITAS VOLUME:4 ISSUE: 1]]></page><page Index="71"><![CDATA[Infographics                                                                                                  65]]></page><page Index="72"><![CDATA[E








                     A








                      T









                     U








                     R








                      E





















        A R T I C L E S]]></page><page Index="73"><![CDATA[67

                AUTHOR:                     “EATABLES WHEN BAKED

            MS. NEHA JAIN                   OR DEEP FRY LEADS TO


             PVT. FORENSIC                  TOXICITY HIGH”

       LECTURER AND TUTOR

                                             INTRODUCTION



      DID YOU                                Eatable  items,  especially  bakery  products,  are  consumed
                                             globally  in  either  baked  or  fried  form  by  subjecting  to  a
      KNOW ??
                                             wide  variety  of  thermal  processes  like  evaporation,
          Toasting bread to a light
                                             pasteurization,  drying,  sterilization,  steaming,  cooking,
        brown color, rather than a
         dark brown color, lowers            boiling, roasting, etc., which may lead to certain chemical
        the amount of acrylamide             changes  in  such  items  due  to  the  formation  of  numerous
                                             toxic        compounds            such         as        acrylamide,

       The  substance  is  formed            hydroxymethylfurfural, and their derivatives. Out of these,

       during  the  process  of              acrylamide  is  considered  to  be  one  of  the  highly  toxic
       baking,  frying,  or  grilling        compounds  known  for  its  potential  carcinogenic

       certain foods that are rich           properties.

       in    carbohydrates        and
       potato-based              items       Toxicity Among Humans

       (French        fries,     chilli
       potatoes,  potato  chips,             Acrylamide causes adverse effects on the nervous system

       cookies,  biscuits,  bread,           that  may  lead  to  neurotoxicity,  muscle  weakness,

       etc.)    at     temperatures          numbness in hands and feet, sweating, unsteadiness, and
       above  120  °C  and  in  low          clumsiness. The toxicant also leads to genetic toxicity and

       humidity  conditions.  This           affects  the  ability  to  produce  offspring,  thereby  causing

       occurs  due  to  a  toxic             reproductive  and  developmental  toxicity.  This  chemical
       chemical  reaction,  namely           contaminant  can  enter  the  body  directly  through  the

       the     Maillard      reaction        respiratory tract, digestive tract, skin, and other ways.

       between  the  bakery  item
       containing           reducing         Acrylamide  enters  the  human  body  through  ingestion,

       carbohydrates        (glucose,        inhalation, and skin, and after inhalation, it gets rapidly
       fructose,  etc.)  and  amino          distributed  to  all  organs  of  the  body  through  the

       acids               (especially       bloodstream. The presence of acrylamide can be identified

       asparagine),  which  results          in the brain, heart, liver, kidneys, and breast milk during
       in  the  formation  of  a             examination.

       specific  taste  and  color
       (browning/frying).
                                          VERITAS VOLUME:4 ISSUE: 1]]></page><page Index="74"><![CDATA[68

      Metabolism of Acrylamide

                                                                      Using  bred  wheat  genotypes
      The  toxic  chemical  gets  metabolized  inside                 having  low  levels  of  amino  acid

      the  body  to  a  reactive  epoxide  via  a                     asparagine  by  using  the  enzyme

      catalyzed      reaction     fostered      by     the            asparaginase          to       hydrolyse
      cytochrome        enzyme,      which       converts             asparagine  to  aspartic  acid  and

      acrylamide  to  an  AA  reactive,  mutagenic,                   ammonia prior to cooking.

      and genotoxic compound, glycidamide.                            Utilization      of    some      modern
                                                                      processes,  like  steam  baking,

      The  Department  of  Health  and  Human                         microwave baking, etc., for baking
      Services (DHHS), the International Agency                       or  using  methods  that  involve

      for  Research  on  Cancer  (IARC),  and  the                    radio  frequency  and  an  inert

      EPA  have  concluded  that  acrylamide  is                      atmosphere  during  the  baking
      likely  to  be  carcinogenic  to  humans,  based                process.

      on sufficient evidence of cancer in animals.                    Application  of  some  inhibitory

                                                                      substances,  like  applying  glycine
      Suggestive  Measures  for  Reduction  of                        and glutamine to the dough before

      Acrylamide Formation                                            fermentation  or  the  use  of

                                                                      bacteriocin-like              inhibitory
      The  formation  of  these  toxic  compounds                     substances  producing  lactic  acid

      cannot  be  completely  stopped  during  the                    bacteria.
      process  of  baking  or  deep-frying,  but  the

      production  of  these  chemicals  can  be                  FDA Guidelines

      reduced      by    adopting       the    following
      measures:                                                  As  acrylamide  is  found  primarily  in

                                                                 potato-based  foods  and  cereal-based
          Modifying the product formulations                     foods,  the  FDA  advises  the  public  to

          Modifying  the  processing  conditions,                adopt a healthy diet plan free of fried

          including  lowering  the  pH,  baking                  foods,  which  can  limit  the  acrylamide
          temperature, and time.                                 intake.  The  FDA  emphasizes  fruits,

          Addition  of  certain  food  ingredients               vegetables,  whole  grains,  and  fat-free
          that  have  tried  to  minimise  or  inhibit           or  low-fat  milk  and  milk  products  in

          acrylamide  formation  (organic  acids,                the  diet,  along  with  the  inclusion  of

          mainly  citric,  calcium,  or  magnesium               lean  meats,  poultry,  fish,  beans,  eggs,
          ions,  and  extracts  with  antioxidant                and nuts.

          properties)



                                       VERITAS VOLUME:4 ISSUE: 1]]></page><page Index="75"><![CDATA[69


       REFERENCES



            Program, H. F. (2017, December                                 Min Fan et al, Toxicity, formation,

            11). FDA issues final guidance for                             contamination, determination and
            industry on how to reduce                                      mitigation of acrylamide in

            acrylamide in certain foods. U.S.                              thermally processed plant-based

            Food And Drug Administration.                                  foods and herbal medicines: A
            https://www.fda.gov/food/hfp-                                  review. Ecotoxicology and

            constituent-updates/fda-issues-                                Environmental Safety, Volume
            final-guidance-industry-how-                                   260, 2023, 115059, ISSN 0147-

            reduce-acrylamide-certain-foods                                6513,

                                                                           https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ecoenv.20
            Agency for Toxic Substances and                                23.115059.

            Disease Registry. (2012).
            Acrylamide- ToxFAQsTM

            [ToxFAQs].

            http://www.atsdr.cdc.gov/toxfaqs/i
            ndex.asp




            Sarion, C., Codină, G. G., &
            Dabija, A. (2021). Acrylamide in

            bakery Products: A review on

            health risks, legal regulations and
            strategies to reduce its formation.

            International Journal of
            Environmental Research and

            Public Health, 18(8), 4332.

            https://doi.org/10.3390/ijerph18084
            332





















                                       VERITAS VOLUME:4 ISSUE: 1]]></page><page Index="76"><![CDATA[70
            AUTHOR:  ROSHNI                    EXPLORING TRUE


            STUDENT, RRIMS                     HERMAPHRODITE AND ITS

            RR INSTITUTE OF                    MEDICO-LEGAL


       MANAGEMENT STUDIES,                     COMPLEXITIES

               BANGALORE



                                                 ABSTRACT



                                                 True hermaphrodites are the most uncommon form of

      DID YOU                                    the  disorder  of  sexual  differentiation  (DSD),
                                                 accounting for about 5% of all cases, based on 67 cases
       KNOW ??
                                                 with  clear  documentation  reported  on  illustration  of
         Hermaphrodites can be                   their chromosomal studies, whilst 90% of the time, the

        born from fusion of an XX                normal chromosomal profile carries 46XX karyotype.
       embryo with a XY embryo, a
                                                 The  basic  body  design  and  many  of  its  structural
      very rare phenomena called
                                                 distinctions between males and hermaphrodites are the
                Chimerism
                                                 same,  even  though  many  sex-specific  differences

                                                 influence  the  majority  of  tissues,  which  suggests  that
        INTRODUCTION
                                                 they  have  both  comparable  and  distinctive  ways  of

                                                 experiencing things. The basic body design and many
        The      key     distinguishing
                                                 of  its  structural  distinctions  between  males  and
        feature of hermaphroditism               hermaphrodites  are  the  same,  despite  the  fact  that

        is  that  each  individual  can          there  are  many  sex-specific  differences  that  influence
        (at  least  potentially)  gain           the majority of tissues, which suggests that they have

        fitness  through  both  male             both comparable and distinctive ways of experiencing

        and  female  reproduction,               things.
        either  by  adopting  the  two
                                                 (Keywords: Hermaphrodite, karyotype, DSD)
        sexes       sequentially       or

        simultaneously.  The  person
        may            have           XX
                                                  There are four different types of hermaphroditism, as
        chromosomes,                  XY
                                                  follows:  (a)  46,  XX  hermaphroditism;  (b)  46,  XY
        chromosomes, or both. The
                                                  hermaphroditism; (c) complex hermaphroditism.
        external        genitalia       in
                                                  An individual with true gonadal hermaphroditism has
        hermaphrodites  may  be
                                                  both ovarian and testicular tissue, either in the same
        ambiguous  or  may  appear
                                                  gonad  (referred  to  as  ovotestes)  or  in  one  testis  and
        to be male or female.
                                                  one ovary.



                                       VERITAS VOLUME:4 ISSUE: 1]]></page><page Index="77"><![CDATA[71

     METHOD                                                         Although the signs of the surgery are
                                                                    not  completely  sealed  off,  due  to  this

     The  methods  used  for  the  examination  of                  they  face  problems  maintaining  the

     hermaphrodites  are  surgery  after  the  proper               dignity  of  inter-relationships,  which
     examination  of  the  patient  and  consultation               causes psychological distress in them.

     with  the  parents.  Most  of  the  time,  surgery  is

     recommended  just  after  the  birth  to  be                    REFERENCES
     performed  because  adult  patients  may  or  may

     not  suffer  from  the  side  effects  of  surgery  on                Krob, G., Braun, A., & Kuhnle, U.
     sexual  responsiveness.  Many  new  guidelines                       (1994). True hermaphroditism:

     have been implemented to prohibit any surgery                        Geographical distribution, clinical

     that is conducted for social reasons.                                findings, chromosomes and gonadal
                                                                          histology. European Journal of

     RESULT                                                               Pediatrics, 153(1), 2–10.
                                                                          https://doi.org/10.1007/bf0200077

     Based  on  case  reports  and  research,  different

     types of hermaphrodites are classified depending                     Rangecroft, L. (2003). Surgical
     on  the  number  of  sex  chromosomes.  The                          management of ambiguous genitalia.

     different  surgical  methods  (gonadectomy)  are                     Archives of Disease in Childhood,

     performed  on  the  patients  with  the  concern  of                 88(9), 799–801.
     parents and respective medical experts.                              https://doi.org/10.1136/adc.88.9.799




     DISCUSSION                                                           Carpenter and J. A. Rock. New
                                                                          York: Raven Press, p. 95, 1992

     The  individual  born  without  a  clear  male  or
     female  phenotype  comes  under  the  disorder  of                   Money, J., Hampson, J. G., &

     sexual  differentiation.  The  success  of  surgery                  Hampson, J. L. (2018, December 1).

     depends  on  a  rapid  and  precise  diagnosis  and                  Hermaphroditism: recommendations
     appropriate  gender  assignment  with  proper                        concerning assignment of sex,

     medical therapy.                                                     change of sex and psychologic
                                                                          management.

     CONCLUSION                                                           https://www.unboundmedicine.com/

                                                                          medline/citation/13260819/Hermaph
     Hermaphrodites  face  many  problems,  such  as                      roditism:_recommendations_concern

     infertility, disclosure, different body image, and                   ing_assignment_of_sex_change_of_s

     many  more.  With  the  concern  of  medical                         ex_and_psychologic_management_
     experts, they go for surgery.



                                       VERITAS VOLUME:4 ISSUE: 1]]></page><page Index="78"><![CDATA[72












                  Hermaphroditism: recommendations

                  concerning assignment of sex,

                  change of sex and psychologic
                  management. (1955b, October 1).

                  PubMed.
                  https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/132

                  60819/



                  Queer phenomenology: orientation,

                  objects, others. Durham and

                  London: Duke University
                  Press. https://read.dukeupress.edu/bo

                  oks/book/1065/Queer-

                  PhenomenologyOrientations-
                  Objects-Others



                  WILSON, E. B. (1911). The sex

                  chromosomes. Arch. Mikrosk. Anat.

                  77, Abt 11, 249-
                  271https://www.nature.com/scitable/

                  content/16248/FASEB_McKusic.pdf

































                                       VERITAS VOLUME:4 ISSUE: 1]]></page><page Index="79"><![CDATA[73

         AUTHOR: PRIYANKA                   THE ROLE OF DIGITAL


                 GHOSH                      FORENSICS IN
                                            CRYPTOCURRENCY


                                            CRIMES: TURNING A NEW
      DID YOU
                                            PAGE IN THE FIELD OF

      KNOW ??
                                            FINANCE

              The person or
       organisation who created              INTRODUCTION
       bitcoin is yet unkown and
         goes by a public given
                                             Cryptocurrencies have evolved from being a subgroup to a
       name “Satoshi Nakamoto”
                                             dominant force in the modern-day financial sector, wying

                                             up  for  a  large  market  from  legitimate  investors  and
                                             cybercriminals. There have been no crimes associated with
        Cryptocurrency  Crimes  are
                                             any of the digital currencies that pop up, as in the case of
        on the Rise
                                             Bitcoin, Ethereum etc. Gone are the days of identifying a

                                             mere  case  of  fraud,  as  the  terminology  has  now  gone  a
        Cyberspace  is  a  popular
                                             notch  higher  to  border  on  serious  constructs  like  anti-
        destination       for     digital
                                             terrorist  financing  and  counterintelligence.  This  is  where
        currencies,  which  simplify
                                             digital forensics comes to play as it helps deal with crimes
        transactions        but       are
                                             related to cryptocurrencies.
        originally     extensions      of
        common  currencies.  These

        records  are  public  and
        accessible  through  block

        explorers,  but  the  actual

        users  are  shielded  behind
        aliases,    offering     various

        benefits to users on the run,

        especially criminals.
        Cryptocurrencies              are

        attractive to criminals for a

        variety  of  petty  crimes
        including  fraud,  large-scale

        drug  trafficking  &  human                           Image 1: This shows an image of Bitcoin
        trafficking.





                                       VERITAS VOLUME:4 ISSUE: 1]]></page><page Index="80"><![CDATA[74

      The  Importance  of  Digital  Forensics  in  the             Dark Web Investigation: The dark web
      Context  of  the  Exchange  of  Crypto                       provides a lot of useful opportunities to

      Currencies                                                   perform          illegal       cryptocurrency
                                                                   transactions  such  as  drug  trafficking,

      Digital     forensics     is    crucial     in    the        weapon  selling,  and  illegal  services.

      identification  of  online  traces  left  by                 Digital  forensics  specialists  are  often
      offenders  in  the  field  of  cryptocurrencies.             seeking  ways  to  penetrate  dark  web

      Investigators  use  expertise,  tools,  and                  markets  and  other  platforms  to  collect
      creativity       to     track      cryptocurrency            information  about  criminal  operations.

      transactions,  despite  encryption  layers                   Tracing  these  transactions  back  into

      hiding them.                                                 these  markets  makes  it  possible  to  do
                                                                   the mapping of the organization and the

           Blockchain            Analysis,         Wallet          criminal acts within it.

           Identification,        and        Attribution:          Ransomware  Attack  Investigations:
           Blockchain analysis is a method used by                 Digital forensics is playing an important

           forensic experts to trace cryptocurrency                role  in  the  tracking  of  cryptocurrency

           crimes. It involves analysing blockchain                payments  made  in  the  form  of  ransom
           transactions       to    understand        their        in  cases  related  to  ransomware.

           architecture,  flow  direction,  patterns,              Analysing this financial movement from
           and  address  links.  Advanced  analysis                the victim's digital wallet to that of the

           uses  databases  like  Exchange  Database               criminal,      and     further      into    any

           for  identification.  Blockchain  addresses             subsequent  transactions,  might  help
           are     often     associated      with     each         identify  the  perpetrators  or  their

           cryptocurrency,  as  funds  can  only  be               accomplices.  The  work  helps  retrieve
           accessed  with  private  keys  stored  in               some  stolen  money  or  locates  certain

           wallets.  By  analysing  blockchain  and                crime groups.

           cryptocurrency  transactions,  forensic                 Seizing and Recovering Assets: A major
           specialists can track wallets involved in               obstacle  that  it  faces  is  the  absence  of

           a  crime  and  restrict  their  use  by                 asset     seizure      and      recovery      in

           identifying  the  criminal  purpose  of  the            cryptocurrency-related  crimes.  Unlike
           wallet and that of an exchange.                         traditional           bank           accounts,

                                                                   cryptocurrencies  can  be  moved  in  an

                                                                   instant      and     anonymously         across
                                                                   borders.  However,  forensic  experts  can

                                                                   work with exchanges and other players
                                                                   to  freeze  wallets  and  recover  siphoned

                                                                   funds.



                                       VERITAS VOLUME:4 ISSUE: 1]]></page><page Index="81"><![CDATA[75
                                                                 With      ever-increasing      cryptocurrency
       Challenges and Future Directions
                                                                 integration       into     global      financial
                                                                 frameworks,  upholding  the  integrity  of
       Digital         forensics        relative        to
                                                                 this  emerging  domain  makes  digital
       cryptocurrency-related             crimes        is
                                                                 forensics  very  important.  Through
       challenged  in  multiple  ways  due  to  rapid
                                                                 continuous            innovation             and
       technological       advancements,        privacy-
                                                                 collaboration,      forensic     experts     are
       oriented coins such as Monero and Zcash,
                                                                 working  toward  ensuring  that  the
       and  the  use  of  mixers  and  tumblers  to
                                                                 promise  of  cryptocurrencies  is  not
       obscure  the  path  of  transactions.  Due  to
                                                                 tarnished  by  illegal  activities  which  it
       the  decentralized  and  global  nature  of
                                                                 might make possible.
       cryptocurrencies,  international  login  is
       frequently  required  to  progress  any  type
                                                                    REFERENCES
       of  investigation.  Legal  frameworks  and
       regulatory measures are falling behind the
                                                                         McNew, S. (n.d.). How
       rapidly  changing  technology,  allowing
                                                                         Cryptocurrency Intersects with
       opportunities       for     cybercriminals       to
                                                                         Fraud Investigations. FTI
       exploit.  The  future  of  digital  forensics  in
                                                                         Technology.
       the     field     of    cryptocurrency-related
                                                                         https://www.ftitechnology.com/
       cybercrime        would       suggest      further
                                                                         resources/blog/how-
       development  of  sophisticated  analytical
                                                                         cryptocurrency-intersects-with-
       tools,  greater  collaborative  effort  on
                                                                         fraud-investigations
       behalf  of  law  enforcement,  and  legal
                                                                         Dudani, S., Baggili, I.,
       frameworks  to  address  the  complexity  of
                                                                         Raymond, D., & Marchany, R.
       cybercrime. Just as the cryptocurrency will
                                                                         (2023). The current state of
       continue to develop and change over time,
                                                                         cryptocurrency forensics.
       so  too  will  the  approaches  and  methods
                                                                         Forensic Science International
       for countering the crimes associated with
                                                                         Digital Investigation, 46,
       such technology.
                                                                         301576.

                                                                         https://doi.org/10.1016/j.fsidi.20
       CONCLUSION
                                                                         23.301576



       Digital  forensics  plays  a  critical  role  in
       fighting cryptocurrency-related crimes and

       gives  essential  tools  and  knowledge  to

       track,  examine,  and  disrupt  illegitimate
       networks functioning within the realms of

       digital currency.


                                       VERITAS VOLUME:4 ISSUE: 1]]></page><page Index="82"><![CDATA[76

         AUTHOR: ANOHA ANN                  DECIPHERING THE HIDDEN:

                 CHERIAN                    AN ANALYSIS OF INVISIBLE


                                            DOTS ON PRINTED
                                            DOCUMENTS

        DID YOU

        KNOW ??                              INTRODUCTION



        The existence of MIC was
                                             A tiny dot can reveal the truth. It can lead an investigator
        not known to public until
                                             to  a  suspect.  These  invisible  dots,  found  in  printed
        2004, even though Xerox
        and Canon started using it           documents,  assist  in  tracking  specific  details  such  as  the

             since mid 1980s                 date  and  time  of  printing,  the  serial  number,  and  the
                                             location of the printer, which can help identify the culprit.
                                             This  article  explores  the  analysis  and  decryption  of  the
        HISTORY                              hidden dots on printed documents.

                                             The  printed  paper  contains  hidden  dots  that  are  visible

        Printer     manufacturers            under blue light, UV, and IR. Under blue light, the dots
        introduced tracking dots             typically  appear  as  a  small  yellow  dot  pattern,  providing

        on printed documents in              important  case-related  information.  These  dots  are
        the      mid-1980s         in        commonly  referred  to  as  Machine  Identification  Code

        collaboration  with  the             (MIC).

        US  government  to  spot
        counterfeit     and      fake

        documents                like

        certificates, bond papers,
        bills, and cheques. In the

        1980s,  the  U.S.  Secret

        Service  worked  with  the
        Japanese  Ministry  of

        Finance  to  tackle  the
                                                     Image 1 :MIC code under white Light & Blue Light
        problem  of  counterfeit                     https://www.snopes.com/fact-check/household-printers-tracking-

        currencies  made  using                      code/

        color  copiers,  leading
        copier  manufacturers  to            These  codes  are  crucial  in  forensics  while  dealing  with

        agree to include machine             questioned documents. The yellow dots are arranged in a
        identification codes.                15 x 8 grid pattern.






                                       VERITAS VOLUME:4 ISSUE: 1]]></page><page Index="83"><![CDATA[77



       ANALYSIS



       1.Materials required-

       Questioned  sample,  blue  light,  UV
       light/IR, and microscope.

       2.Procedure-
            The     questioned       sample     is
                                                                    Image 2: Machine Identification Code (Yellow
            observed  under the microscope
                                                                    Dots)
            under blue light.                                       https://www.bbc.com/future/article/20170607-
            Analyze  the  yellow  dot  pattern                      why-printers-add-secret-tracking-dots

            present on the sample.

            Observe the sequence of dots.                      In the image above, each row represents
            Note these observations.                           data:

       3.Decoding the MIC code                                   1. The  first  vertical  row  displays

       Decoding  the  information  involves                        numbers in a sequence: 64, 32, 16, 8,
       illuminating  the  printed  page  with                      4,  2,  and  1.  This  row  is  known  as

       blue  light  to  make  the  yellow  dots                    'row parity'.
       more  visible.  Then  the  page  is                       2. The  first  horizontal  row  shows

       captured      in    a    high-resolution                    numbers in sequence: 1, 2, 3, 4,... to

       photograph or scan, typically at 600                        15.  This  row  is  known  as  'column
       dpi or higher. The resulting image is                       parity'.

       then  processed  using  specialised                       3. The  2nd  and  5th  vertical  rows
       software  designed  to  analyze  the                        indicate  the  time,  with  the  2nd

       dot  pattern  and  convert  it  into                        representing  minutes  and  the  5th

       binary  code.  This  binary  code  is                       representing hours.
       then     translated      into     human-                  4. The  6th,  7th,  and  8th  vertical  rows

       readable  information  based  on  the                       represent  day,  month,  and  year,

       known  structure  of  the  tracking                         respectively.
       code grid.                                                5. The 10th, 11th, 12th, 13th, and 14th

                                                                   vertical  rows  encode  the  unique
                                                                   serial  number  of  the  printer  in

                                                                   binary form.
                                                                 6. The 3rd, 4th, 9th, and 15th vertical

                                                                   rows  remain  unknown  and  are  not

                                                                   used when decoding the code.




                                       VERITAS VOLUME:4 ISSUE: 1]]></page><page Index="84"><![CDATA[78


      To  decode  the  MIC,  the  dot

      sequence       must       be     carefully
      examined because the codes denote

      binary digits that include vital case-
      related  information.  The  codes  are

      made  by  arranging  dots  in  a  grid,

      each dot indicating a binary system
                                                                    Image 3: Decoding MIC
      that  conveys  information.  The
                                                                    https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Printertrackingdo
      presence  or  lack  of  a  dot  in  a                         ts

      specific grid location corresponds to
      "1"  or  "0"  in  binary  code,  which

      denotes  information  such  as  the

      printer's serial number and the date                     CONCLUSION
      and time of the printed page.

                                                               The  presence  of  yellow  dots  in  printed
      Examine  the  6th,  7th,  and  8th                       paper  is  a  significant  improvement  in

      vertical  rows  in  the  given  image.                   forensic        investigation        methods,

      The three dots in the 6th row (day)                      especially  in  tracking  the  source  of
      represent  the  digits  15,  4,  and  1.                 printed      documents.        These      dots,

      These digits (15+4+1=21) add up to                       discreetly  embedded  by  color  laser
      the  21st  day.  Two  dots  in  the  7th                 printers  and  copiers,  contain  encoded

      row  (month)  represent  the  digits  4                  data  like  the  printer's  serial  number,

      and 2, which add up to 6, indicating                     time,  and  potentially  other  identifying
      the  6th  month.  Similarly,  the  8th                   information.

      row      (year),    with      two     dots

      corresponding to the numbers 4 and                       From a forensic view, this technology is
      1, is added to give 5, indicating the                    a critical tool for establishing the chain

      year 2005.                                               of  custody  in  legal  proceedings.  By

                                                               decoding these yellow dots, investigators
      The  decoding  process  revealed  the                    can  accurately  connect  a  document  to

      printing  date  of  the  specific                        the  specific  printer  or  copier  used  to
      document to be '21-06-2005', based                       create it, thus confirming its authenticity

      on the information in the 6th, 7th,                      and  helping  in  the  reconstruction  of

      and 8th rows.                                            events.






                                       VERITAS VOLUME:4 ISSUE: 1]]></page><page Index="85"><![CDATA[79




             REFERENCES



                 DocuColor Tracking Dot

                 Decoding Guide.
                 (n.d.).https://w2.eff.org/Privacy/pri

                 nters/docucolor/#program



                 Dookeran, J. (2024, June 14). How

                 your printer leaves invisible
                 tracking codes on every page.

                 How-To Geek.

                 https://www.howtogeek.com/how-
                 your-printer-leaves-invisible-

                 tracking-codes-on-every-page/



























































                                       VERITAS VOLUME:4 ISSUE: 1]]></page><page Index="86"><![CDATA[80
                                            THE HAZE OF MEMORY:


         AUTHOR: HAMSA J                    ALCOHOL INTOXICATION

                                            IMPACT ON EYEWITNESS

                                            MEMORY




        DID YOU
                                            INTRODUCTION
        KNOW ??

                                            Forensic psychology involves making use of psychological
       Cerebral cortex is the first
       part where alcohol affects           practices  and  theories  throughout  a  case  and  assisting

            brain. Conscious                police officers and legal authorities during the process of
        thoughts, language and              interrogation of the suspect, the victim, and the witnesses.
          interaction is under              Forensic  psychologists  often  indulge  in  conducting
           control of this part             psychological  evaluations  of  individuals.  These  reports


                                            given  by  forensic  psychologists  provide  support  in  legal
                                            proceedings for decision-making.



        Eyewitnesses  are  one  of

        the few people present at
        the  scene  of  the  crime

        who  witness  the  whole

        crime  scene.  They  are
        usually  treated  with  the

        utmost  care  to  protect                          Image 1:Few terms used in forensic psychology

        the  crucial  information                          Forensic-Psychology-pinterest.jpg (1600×1197)
                                                           (degreequery.com)
        they  possess  regarding

        the  crime  that  occurred,          FACTORS  THAT  AFFECT  THE  EYEWITNESS’S
        and  the  sequence  of  the          MEMORY

        events,  and  in  some

        cases,  they  might  even            In  many  cases,  right  after  eyewitnesses  are  found  at  the
        help  in  identifying  the           crime scene, the investigating officers often make sure that

        suspect.                             all  the  witnesses  are  placed  in  different  locations  away

                                             from each other. The presence of another co-witness with

                                             them has always led to a misunderstanding of the events
                                             and  the  information,  which  acts  as  a  hindrance  in  the

                                             investigation  and  eventually  ruins  the  whole  court

                                             proceeding.


                                       VERITAS VOLUME:4 ISSUE: 1]]></page><page Index="87"><![CDATA[81




       All  eyewitnesses  who  might  have                     Influence of level of alcohol intoxication:
       visualized  a  heinous  crime  have                     A case study

       always reported being in a state of

       mental  shock  and  acute  stress,                      A study conducted by Ms Georgina and
       which  forces  them  to  forget  the                    the group had 67 participants who were

       information  that  is  required  the                    administered  different  amounts  of
       most.  [²]  Intake  of  drugs  and                      alcohol,  and  they  were  shown  2  videos

       alcohol  also  plays  a  major  role  in                and  were  told  to  recall  after  the

       the     alteration      of     eyewitness               consumption  of  alcohol.  The  result  of
       memory.                                                 this  study  helped  the  group  to  know

                                                               more  about  the  behavior  of  alcohol  in

       Effects  of  alcohol  intoxication  on                  the human brain.
       eyewitness

                                                               The  higher  the  level  of  acute  alcohol

       Individuals          questioned          as             intoxication,  the  lower  the  level  of
       ‘eyewitnesses’ often receive pressure                   confidence  and  also  in  their  mental

       from  the  investigators  and  society;                 stability.  They  eventually  decided  that
       reports have been made stating that                     with  an  increase  in  the  amount  of

       the eyewitnesses were intoxicated by                    alcohol  consumption,  the  poorer  the

       alcohol or any kind of psychoactive                     accuracy  of  the  information  perceived
       substance,  which  eventually  makes                    by  them.  In  some  cases,  due  to  high

       them  feel  less  nervous,  but  this                   levels  of  intoxication,  the  participants
       intake of alcohol has always proven                     even  said  ‘I  don’t  know,’  to  certain

       to alter their memory.                                  questions.  In  the  end,  they  concluded

                                                               that  this  study  was  also  filled  with
       A  review  of  laboratory  tests  and                   limitations  such  as  the  tolerance  of

       surveys  has  stated  that  acute                       alcohol,  mental  state,  the  delayed

       alcohol  intoxication  impairs  the                     response  of  the  participants,  and  the
       memory  of  a  person;  it  doesn’t                     influence of co-witnesses. The real-world

       necessarily impair the main memory                      scenarios  play  a  major  role,  which

       or  the  unconscious  memory,  but  it                  cannot be achieved through a study. [⁴]
       does  affect  the  memory  that  is

       affected  by  stress  or  certain
       memories  that  are  registered  as

       undesirable by the human brain. [³]]]></page><page Index="88"><![CDATA[82





          CONCLUSION



          Many  factors  affect  the  memory  and  the  reliability  of  eyewitnesses.  Alcohol

          intoxication  is  one  of  the  neglected  factors  that  have  a  major  effect  on  their
          memory  based  on  the  amount  of  consumption.  If  all  the  required  conditions

          that are necessary for eyewitness testimony are satisfied, it can be said that it

          could prove to be conclusive evidence.









                 REFERENCES



                     Wulff, A. N., & Thomas, A. K.

                     (2021). The dynamic and fragile
                     nature of eyewitness memory

                     formation: considering stress and
                     attention. Frontiers in Psychology,

                     12.

                     https://doi.org/10.3389/fpsyg.2021.6
                     66724




                     APA PsycNet. (n.d.).
                     https://psycnet.apa.org/record/2022-

                     78063-001



                     APA PsycNet. (n.d.-b).

                     https://psycnet.apa.org/record/2008-
                     01780-007]]></page><page Index="89"><![CDATA[83

             AUTHOR: ANNIE                     SPORTS TOXICOLOGY-

                  SHERIN A                     DETECTION OF DOPING IN

                                               SPORTS




        DID YOU
                                              INTRODUCTION
        KNOW ??

                                              Sports  toxicology  is  defined  as  the  application  of
           Anabolic steroid is the
                                              toxicology or toxicological analysis in preventing unfair
           most abused drugs by
              athletes, which is              means in sports.
           structurally similar to            One  of  the  most  paramount  entities  in  establishing  an
                testosterone                  equitable  zealous  aura  for  athletes  is  the  detection  of

                                              doping.  The  World  Anti-Doping  Agency  and  various
                                              anti-doping  associations  carry  out  the  detection  of

        Doping in sports                      doping and decide the kind of test the athletes should be
                                              tested for, resulting in a doping test either affirmative or

                                              non-affirmative.
        Doping  is  defined  as  an
        unlawful          act         of

        administration       of     any
        illegal or prohibited drugs

        or    substances       by    an

        athlete  to  enhance  his/her
        sports  performance  to

        gain  an  advantage  over

        competitors.
        For      years     now,     the

        utilization  of  substances

        that enhance performance
        (PEDs) in sports has been

        outlawed,                   but                     Image 1: A picture depicting an athlete
                                                            indulged in doping
        transgression still persists.

        Doping  in  athletics  began

        in  the  1920s,  and  despite            This issue is a crucial global challenge, menacing the
        the  efforts  to  curb  it,              integrity of sports competitions and ruining athletes’

        doping has advanced with                 health as well as their eventual deaths.
        time.




                                       VERITAS VOLUME:4 ISSUE: 1]]></page><page Index="90"><![CDATA[84

         The world anti-doping agency’s (WADA) list of forbidden materials and procedures










































        Anti- doping in drug screening


         1. Collection  of  samples  of  blood  and  urine  is  done  at  any  moment  and  place  for

            doping management.
         2. The athlete is informed by the Office of Doping Control (DOC) regarding the choice

            of  doping  management.  A  paper  attesting  to  the  athlete’s  understanding  of  their
            rights and obligations should be autographed by the athlete.

         3. The athlete must present himself to the doping control station at the earliest.

         4. The athlete needs to choose a collection container from the options given.
         5. Not less than 90 ml of urine or blood is collected by the DCO or chaperone of the

            same sex.
         6. Among the sample collection kits given, the athlete needs to choose one of them.

         7. Divide the sample into two bottles, I and II.

         8. First, fill urine/blood up to the mark in bottle II, followed by bottle I, and retain a
            small amount in the collection container.

         9. Close both bottles I and II carefully.

        10. The specific gravity of the sample is measured by the DCO to ensure the sample isn’t
            overly diluted for the analysis.

        11. The athlete needs to sign and complete the doping form.

        12. The samples will be forwarded to a laboratory approved by WADA for analysis at
            rigorous discretion.]]></page><page Index="91"><![CDATA[85




         Techniques used in analysis of doping                    REFERENCES




         The  techniques  that  are  utilized  to                   Niekerk, W. van (Ed.). (n.d.). Drugs and
         identify  steroids,  narcotics,  stimulants,               anti-doping in Sport. Physiopedia.

         masking agents, contaminants of dietary                    https://www.physio-
         supplements, and other materials on the                    pedia.com/Drugs_and_Anti-

         WADA-banned portal are:                                    Doping_in_Sport



                                                                    Microsampling, N. (2024, February 22).

           1. High-sensitivity gas                                  Anti-doping in drug screening: How it

              chromatography-mass spectrometry                      works. Anti-Doping in Drug Screening:
           2. GC-Nitrogen-Phosphorus Detector                       How It Works.

           3. Immunoanalysis (ELISA)                                https://www.neoteryx.com/microsamplin

           4. Advanced liquid-chromatography                        g-blog/anti-doping-in-drug-screening-
              mass spectrometry                                     how-it-works

           5. Mass-spectrometry
           6. Iso Electrofocusing with double                       Carey, K. (n.d.). The detection of doping

              blotting                                              in sport and the role of forensic science.

           7. Longitudinal profiling (‘biological                   Digital Commons @ LIU.
              passport’)                                            https://digitalcommons.liu.edu/post_hon
                                                                    ors_theses/19

         CONCLUSION
                                                                    Botrè, F. (2008). New and old challenges


         According  to  WADA,  24,430  samples                      of sports drug testing. Journal of Mass
         had  been  collected  by  152  anti-doping                 Spectrometry, 43(7), 903–907.

         organizations as of May 2021. In 2020, a                   https://doi.org/10.1002/jms.1455

         total  of  910  anti-doping  infractions
         worldwide       were      observed,       which            Harries, R. L., Paoli, G. D., Hall, S., &

         portrayed a remarkable and noteworthy                      Nisbet, L. A. (2023). Graphical abstract.

         advancement  over  previous  years.  With                  A review of the analytical techniques for
         62  doping  infractions  by  athletes,  India              the detection of anabolic-androgenic

         is  second  in  the  world  for  drug  abuse.              steroids within biological matrices. Wiley
         Educating the athletic community on the                    Interdisciplinary Reviews. Retrieved

         rights, regulations, and doping process is                 from

         pivotal in shaping a doping-free aura for                  https://wires.onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/
         zealous sports.                                            full/10.1002/wfs2.1504.]]></page><page Index="92"><![CDATA[86
       AUTHOR: ABHINANDAN                   REVOLUTIONIZING


           NAGABHUSHANA                     FORENSIC SCIENCE: THE

                                            ROLE OF


      DID YOU                               NANOTECHNOLOGY IN


      KNOW ??                               CRIME SCENE

                                            INVESTIGATION.
         Nanoparticles can be
       highly target specific. This

          makes them efficient                INTRODUCTION
              against cross
        contamination and side                Nanotechnology  in  forensic  science,  termed  nano-
                  effects
                                              forensics, is a completely new area in the field and has

                                              revolutionized key aspects by introducing unprecedented
       What is nanotechnology?                levels  of  sensitivity,  precision,  and  efficiency  in  various

                                              forensic  techniques.  The  use  of  nanotechnology  in
       Nanotechnology is a branch             forensics  can  be  traced  back  to  the  1970s  for  the

       of  science  and  engineering          detection of fingerprints, and since then there have been
       that     deals      with      the      major advancements in its contribution to the field.

       manufacturing,            design,
                                               Application of Nanotechnology in Forensic Science
       synthesis, and application of
       devices       or      structures
                                                 1. Detection  of  fingerprints:  Fingerprints  are  the
       through  the  control  of
                                                    unique  patterns  of  ridges  found  on  the  fingers  of
       matter  ranging  from  1  to
                                                    all  humans.  No  two  humans  will  have  the  same
       100 nanometers in diameter.
                                                    fingerprint  pattern,  not  even  identical  twins.
       For        perspective,          a
                                                    Nanotechnology  has  greatly  advanced  the
       nanometer  is  one-billionth
                                                    detection  of  latent  fingerprints,  which  are
       of a meter, which is around
                                                    fingerprints that are not easily visible to the naked
       100,000  times  smaller  than
                                                    eye.
       the  width  of  a  human  hair.
                                                    Gold and silver nanoparticles: These particles can
       The fundamental concept of
                                                    be functionalised with specific chemicals that bind
       nanotechnology                was
                                                    to components of sweat residue left by fingerprints,
       introduced       by     Richard
                                                    which can then be made visible by emitting light on
       Feynman in 1959.
                                                    the  surface.  Nanoparticles  offer  a  much  higher

                                                    surface-to-area  ratio,  improving  the  sensitivity  of

                                                    fingerprint     detection      methods       than     other
                                                    traditional methods.


                                       VERITAS VOLUME:4 ISSUE: 1]]></page><page Index="93"><![CDATA[87




























            Image  1:  Colorimetric-based  detection  of
                                                                       Image 2: Working of a nanosensor
            latent fingerprints using nanoparticles.


        2.Forensic          toxicological         analysis:
                                                                        Solid Phase Extraction (SPE): This
        Nanotechnology is most effectively used in
                                                                        technique  is  used  to  isolate  and
        the  examination  of  several  different  toxic
                                                                        concentrate toxins from biological
        materials, such as drugs, poison, and other
                                                                        samples.  One  such  example  is  the
        chemicals,      from     forensically      essential
                                                                        use of magnetic nanoparticles like
        biological  evidence  like  hair,  sweat,  blood,
                                                                        iron oxide nanoparticles, including
        sweat, and vitreous humor.
                                                                        magnetite  (Fe203)  and  maghemite
             Nanosensors: These are devices that can
                                                                        (γ-Fe203),  that  can  bind  to  a
             detect  very  minute  concentrations  of
                                                                        unique toxin.
             toxic  substances  in  biological  samples.

             They  use  gold,  silver,  and  titanium
             oxide nanoparticles that detect changes

             in  electric  signals  when  a  toxin  is
             present  or  that  emit  light  when  they

             come  in  contact  with  a  toxin.  These

             nanoparticles are also active and stable,
             and the costs associated with these tools

             are  low;  hence,  they  are  the  major
             substitutes     for     tool    field     tests.

             Nanosensors  are  highly  sensitive  and

             can  provide  immediate  detection  and                   Image 3: Cross-sections of nanotubes and a
             can also determine the concentration of                   nanowire.

             the toxin present.






                                       VERITAS VOLUME:4 ISSUE: 1]]></page><page Index="94"><![CDATA[88







                                                                 Forensic  DNA  Analysis:  This  analysis
           3)Detection          of         Explosives:
                                                                 is carried out in murder cases and rape
           Nanotechnology has become a crucial
                                                                 cases  to  examine  blood  stains,  hair,
           tool  in  the  detection  of  explosives,
                                                                 fibres, semen, etc.
           which  enhances  the  efficiency  of

           detection  methods  and  provides
                                                                 Nanofluidic  devices:  These  devices  are
           innovative approaches for identifying
                                                                 the  most  recent  advances  in  forensic
           explosive      compounds         in    trace
                                                                 DNA  analysis.  Nanofluidics  is  the
           amounts.
                                                                 study  of  behavior,  manipulation,  and

                                                                 control  of  fluids  that  are  confined  to
               Nanowire  and  nanotube  sensors:
                                                                 structures  of  nanometer  dimensions.
               These offer significant advantages
                                                                 These devices can sort and collect DNA
               for  the  detection  and  analysis  of
                                                                 up to a level of one molecule at a time
               explosive  residues.  Due  to  their
                                                                 for further analysis. This method allows
               high  surface  area  and  sensitivity,
                                                                 for shorter examination time and a low
               they  are  effective  at  picking  up
                                                                 risk of contamination of the evidence.
               minute quantities of such residues
               left at crime scenes.




               They  can  also  be  used  in  high-
               resolution  analytical  techniques,

               like  gas  chromatography-mass
               spectroscopy  (GC-MS)  or  liquid

               chromatography-mass

               spectroscopy  (LC-MS),  which
               improve       the    resolution      and

               accuracy  in  identifying  explosive

               compounds.
                                                                    Image 4: Nanofluidic-based DNA sorter.



















                                       VERITAS VOLUME:4 ISSUE: 1]]></page><page Index="95"><![CDATA[89








           CONCLUSION




           Nanotechnology represents a transformative advancement in forensic science,
           offering  remarkable  levels  of  sensitivity,  specificity,  and  precision  in  crime

           scene  investigations  and  evidence  analysis.  As  research  and  development  in
           nanotechnology continue to evolve, its applications in forensic science are set

           to revolutionize the field, leading to more effective crime-solving and justice

           delivery.







             REFERENCES



                  Keshika Dahiya1, Hrishita Sharma2, Largee Biswas3 * & Anita Kamra

                  Verma3 *. (December 2022). Nanotechnology in Forensic Science: Extensive

                  Applications and New Perspective Indian Journal of Biochemistry &
                  Biophysics Vol. 59. Kirori Mal College, University of Delhi, New Delhi-110

                  007, Delhi, India 2 Maitreyi College, University of Delhi, New Delhi-110

                  021, Delhi, India 3 Nano-Biotech Lab, Kirori Mal College, University of
                  Delhi, New Delhi-110 007, Delhi,

                  India.https://nopr.niscpr.res.in/bitstream/123456789/60981/1/IJBB%2059%2

                  812%29%201144-1147.pdf



                  Atul Kumar Dubey, Maninder Kaur*. Development of Latent Fingerprints
                  through Nanoparticles: A Review ARC Journal of Forensic Science

                  Volume 8, Issue 1, (2024) PP 12-16.School of Sciences, Alakh Prakash

                  Goyal Shimla University, Shimla, Himachal Pradesh, India.
                  https://www.arcjournals.org/pdfs/ajfs/v8-i1/3.pdf



                  Richa Rohatgi and Femin Dominica. Application of Nanotechnology in

                  Forensic Science (2024). Department of Forensic Science, Amity

                  University, Haryana, India. https://www.hilarispublisher.com/open-
                  access/application-of-nanotechnology-in-forensic-science.pdf







                                       VERITAS VOLUME:4 ISSUE: 1]]></page><page Index="96"><![CDATA[Infographics | by Ragavi Allakathan and Hansen S. Jerem                                                       90]]></page><page Index="97"><![CDATA[I







                    T






                    E






                    R






                    A






                    T






                    U






                    R







                    E












                     R E V I E W]]></page><page Index="98"><![CDATA[92

        AUTHOR: VANI GUPTA;                 ROLE OF DENTAL


            STUDENT, AMITY                  IMPLANTS IN FORENSIC

      UNIVERSITY NOIDA, UTTAR               IDENTIFICATION

                PRADESH.



                                            INTRODUCTION
      DID YOU

      KNOW ??                               A  key  component  of  forensic  identification  is  frequently

                                            the  ability  to  connect  tangible  evidence  to  a  particular
            Recently, artificial            person. Because every person's dentition is different, dental
          intelligent algorithm is          records  have  long  been  an  essential  part  of  this  process.
         being used to instantly
                                            The  growing  use  of  dental  implants  has  given  forensic
         procure database and
                                            odontology  a  new  facet  in  recent  years.  The  present
         records of all implants.
                                            literature study delves into the significance, methodology,
             One such tool is
               Spotimplant                  and  case  studies  of  dental  implants  in  forensic
                                            identification.

      Dental implants:
      Importance  for  forensic              This  is  especially  true  in  situations  involving  trauma,

      identification                         extensive  decomposition,  or  combustion  when  standard

                                             dental records may be destroyed.
      Dental implants, which are

      artificial                 tooth       Techniques for Recognising Dental Implants
      replacements,  are  usually

      made  of  titanium  and                There are various steps involved in using dental implants

      other           biocompatible          to  identify  a  person.  First,  radiographs  and  photos  are
      materials.                 Their       taken of the implant by forensic odontologists to record its

      robustness,  resilience  to            features.  Implants  frequently  contain  unique  design
                                             elements that can be used to identify them, such as threads
      environmental
                                             and  abutments  and  the  manufacturer's  insignia.  The
      deterioration,  and  distinct
                                             significance  of  thorough  documentation  and  comparison
      production marks set them
                                             with  pre-existing  dental  records  or  implant  databases  is
      apart. These characteristics
                                             emphasised by Sholl et al. (2014).
      make       dental      implants
                                             The  International  Organization  for  Forensic  Odonto-
      highly  useful  for  forensic
                                             Stomatology          (IOFOS),         which       has       produced
      identification, according to
                                             recommendations  for  the  forensic  evaluation  of  dental
      a  study  by  Berketa  et  al.
                                             implants,  is  one  of  the  most  important  sources  on  this
      (2010).
                                             subject.


                                       VERITAS VOLUME:4 ISSUE: 1]]></page><page Index="99"><![CDATA[93


                                                               Obstacles and prospects for the future

      These  recommendations  call  for  a
      methodical  strategy  that  makes  use  of               Dental implants have a well-established role

      dental        implant        registries      and         in  forensic  identification.  However,  there

      radiographic         comparisons.          These         are still issues that need to be resolved. The
      registries,  which  keep  track  of  implant             absence  of  standardized  implant  databases

      serial  numbers  and  patient  data,  have               that  are  available  to  forensic  specialists

      been  useful  in  cross-referencing  and                 globally is one major problem. According to
      verifying  the  identities  of  deceased                 Choi  et  al.  (2016),  the  creation  of  a  global

      people, according to Nagai et al. (2013).                registry      would         improve        forensic

                                                               identification  effectiveness  by  offering  a
      Case  Studies  and  Real-World                           single,  consolidated  source  of  data.

      Implementations                                          Furthermore,        improvements          in     3D
                                                               modeling  and  imaging  technology  could

      The  useful  uses  of  dental  implants  in              lead to an increase in implant identification

      forensic  identification  are  demonstrated              accuracy.  As  recommended  by  Silva  et  al.
      by a multitude of case studies. Berketa et               (2018),  future  research  should  concentrate

      al.  (2012)  described  a  noteworthy                    on  incorporating  these  technologies  into
      instance in which a body recovered from                  forensic processes to improve the resolution

      a  house  fire  was  successfully  identified.           and detail of implant examinations.

      The existence of a dental implant allowed
      forensic scientists to match the implant's               CONCLUSION

      serial  number  with  dental  records,

      conclusively  identifying  the  dead  despite            Dental  implants  are  essential  to  forensic
      the  significant  damage  to  the  bones.                identification  because  they  provide  a

      Baljozovic  et  al.  (2015)  examined  a  case           trustworthy  way  to  identify  people  in

      in  which  several  bodies  were  found  in  a           situations  where  other  approaches  are
      highly  decomposed  form  following  a                   insufficient.  The  distinct  qualities  of

      mass  disaster.  The  capacity  to  quickly              implants,  in  conjunction  with  methodical
      and  accurately  identify  victims  by                   approaches and case studies, highlight their

      comparing  implant  characteristics  with                significance in the field of forensic research.

      dental records was made possible by the                  Dental  implants  will  continue  to  be  an
      existence  of  dental  implants  in  multiple            essential  instrument  in  the  field  of  forensic

      cases,  highlighting  the  effectiveness  and            odontology  if  the  issues  of  database
      dependability  of  this  approach  under                 uniformity  and  technology  integration  are

      trying circumstances.                                    resolved.




                                       VERITAS VOLUME:4 ISSUE: 1]]></page><page Index="100"><![CDATA[94

           REFERENCES


                                                                         Sholl, S. A., Moody, G. H., &
              Deepalakshmi, T., & Prabhakar,
                                                                        Paton, A. (2014).
              M. (2014). Role of dental implants

              in forensic identification. Journal
                                                                        Nagai, T., Yamaguchi, K., &
              of Forensic Dental Sciences, 6(2),
                                                                        Kojima, K. (2013).
              145. https://doi.org/10.4103/0975-

              1475.132546
                                                                        7Baljozovic, M., Belcher, D., &
                                                                        O'Sullivan, D. (2015). Mass
              Radiographic dental implant
                                                                        disaster victim identification
              recognition for geographic
                                                                        using dental implants.
              evaluation in human identification.
                                                                        International Journal of
              (2008, June 1). PubMed.
                                                                        Forensic Odontology, 30(2),
              https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/22
                                                                        101-108.
              689351/

                                                                        Choi, H., Lee, W., & Kim, J.
              Miranda, G. E., Moreira, A. M. C.,
                                                                        (2016). Developing a global
              & Melani, R. F. H. (2019). THE
                                                                        registry for dental implants in
              NEED FOR IMPLANT
                                                                        forensic identification. Journal
              DENTISTS TO KNOW ABOUT
                                                                        of Forensic Research, 7(4),
              THE METHOD OF FORENSIC
                                                                        345-349.
              HUMAN IDENTIFICATION

              USING DENTAL IMPLANTS.
                                                                        Silva, R. F., Pereira, S. D., &
              Revista Brasileira De Odontologia
                                                                        Prado, F. B. (2018). Advances
              Legal, 90–97.
                                                                        in imaging technologies for
              https://doi.org/10.21117/rbol.v6i3.2
                                                                        forensic dental implant
              83
                                                                        identification. Journal of

                                                                        Forensic Imaging, 5, 25-32.
              Survival of batch numbers within
              dental implants following

              incineration as an aid to

              identification. (2010, December 1).
              PubMed.

              https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/21

              239857/







                                       VERITAS VOLUME:4 ISSUE: 1]]></page><page Index="101"><![CDATA[95

           AUTHOR: ADDITIYA                 FORENSIC


              SENGUPTA                      ENTOMOTOXICOLOGY: THE
                                            FUTURE OF

                                            ENTOMOLOGICAL ANALYSIS






      DID YOU

      KNOW ??                               ABSTRACT



          Blow flies can detect a           Forensic  Entomotoxicology  is  a  branch  of  forensic

         dead body from up to 16            entomology  that  utilizes  necrophagous  species  of  insects
       Kms  and are first to reach          that  feed  on  human  carcasses  for  the  detection  and
       the body. Hence, it is most          identification of toxins present in the decomposed corpse.
            studied in forensic
                                            It  deals  with  the  principles  of  forensic  entomology  and
                  analysis
                                            forensic  toxicology.  When  the  body  has  reached  an
                                            advanced  stage  of  decomposition,  where  conventional

                                            biological samples such as urine, blood, tissues, and organs
      INTRODUCTION
                                            cannot  be  recovered  from  the  cadaver  for  toxicological

                                            analysis,  investigators  rely  on  entomological  evidence.
      Forensic entomotoxicology
                                            Arthropods  such  as  flies  and  beetles  that  feed  on  the
      deals  with  the  study  of
                                            xenobiotic substances present in the cadaver, such as drugs
      arthropods          for      the
                                            or  toxins,  are  considered  unconventional  evidence  for
      detection  of  toxins  in
                                            toxicological analysis. The ability of arthropods to retain
      decomposed            carcasses
                                            the  toxicological  indicators  makes  them  an  indispensable
      where             conventional
                                            source  of  forensic  entomological  evidence  and  provides
      biological      samples      are
                                            information  about  the  medical  history  of  the  deceased.
      unavailable                   for
                                            Toxicological  analysis  of  arthropods  helps  determine  the
      toxicological          analysis.      postmortem interval (PMI), time since death, and location
      When  the  body  is  highly           of  the  deceased.  Entomotoxicology  is  useful  in  cases  of

      decomposed,  skeletonised,            poisoning,  homicide,  suicide,  rape,  as  well  as  physical

      or in the presence of burnt           abuse,  which  involves  death  due  to  ingestion  of  toxic
      remains,        which       lack      substances.

      biological  tissues  or  body

      fluids,       analysis         of
      entomological            species

      enables  the  estimation  of

      PMI.


                                       VERITAS VOLUME:4 ISSUE: 1]]></page><page Index="102"><![CDATA[96


                                                             Analysis of Entomotoxicological Evidence


                                                             Drugs  like  barbiturates,  benzodiazepines,
        The  growth  and  development  of
                                                             opiates,  cocaine,  morphine  and  derivatives,
        arthropods         in     entomotoxicology
                                                             illicit       drugs          and          stimulants,
        studies  can  be  affected  by  a  variety  of
                                                             methamphetamine,              heroin,         sodium
        external  factors,  such  as  the  ageing  of
                                                             methohexital,  malathion,  and  methadone  are
        insects,  external  temperature,  weather
                                                             common  drugs  involved.  As  entomological
        conditions, geographical location of the
                                                             evidence shows, the presence of such drugs can
        crime  scene,  contaminants  present  on
                                                             alter  and  affect  the  development  of  larvae;
        the deceased substrate, and quantity of
                                                             during toxicological analysis, such possibilities
        toxin  that  affects  the  development  of
                                                             must  be  considered  to  avoid  errors  while
        the insects. The insects show a varying
                                                             determining PMI.
        absorbing  power  of  xenobiotics  from
                                                             Analysis  of  entomological  evidence  is  carried
        the  cadaver  based  on  the  maturation
                                                             out  using  different  types  of  analytical
        rate of the larvae.
                                                             instruments,         such       as       thin-layered

                                                             chromatography  (TLC),  high-performance
        The  arthropods,  after  being  recovered
                                                             liquid     chromatography           (HPLC),        gas
        from  the  deceased,  are  subjected  to
                                                             chromatography-mass           spectroscopy       (GC-
        homogenization,  after  which  they  are
                                                             MS),  radioimmunoassay  (RIA),  and  liquid
        processed in the same manner as other
                                                             chromatography (LC). A research report that
        biological  tissues  or  body  fluids.
                                                             depicts  the  literature  from  1977  to  2022  (70
        Pharmacokinetics  of  the  drug  depends
                                                             articles)    on     forensic      entomotoxicology
        on  the  feeding  mechanism  and  rate  of
                                                             suggests  that  HPLC,  being  a  versatile
        metabolism of the insects. Factors such
                                                             instrumentation  technique,  can  be  used  in
        as     temperature,        humidity,       and
                                                             entomotoxicological analysis as it is simple to
        radiation  influence  the  stability  and
                                                             operate with minimal sample preparation and
        accumulation of toxins in the tissues of
                                                             high  recovery.  HPLC  can  analyse  soluble
        the     insects.    Blowflies     from      the
                                                             compounds  regardless  of  their  volatility,
        Calliphoridae,          Coleoptera         and
                                                             whereas GC-MS can only analyze volatile and
        Sarcophagidae  families  are  important
                                                             thermally      stable      substances.       Whereas
        insects       studied        in       forensic
                                                             inductively coupled plasma-mass spectroscopy
        entomotoxicology.
                                                             (ICP-MS)  and  inductively  coupled  plasma-
                                                             optical  emission  spectroscopy  (ICP-OES)  are

                                                             used  to  analyse  inorganic  poison  in
                                                             entomological analysis.





                                       VERITAS VOLUME:4 ISSUE: 1]]></page><page Index="103"><![CDATA[97


      Instruments like TLC, GC, and MS are                       REFERENCES
      used  to  examine  the  larvae.  Analysis

      performed on larvae produces efficient                         Campobasso, C. P., Bugelli, V.,
      results  as  compared  to  conventional                        Carfora, A., Borriello, R., & Villet,

      evidence analysis.                                             M. (2019). Advances in

                                                                     entomotoxicology. In CRC Press
      CONCLUSION                                                     eBooks (pp. 287–309).

                                                                     https://doi.org/10.4324/978135116376

      Forensic  entomotoxicology  deals  with                        7-13
      the quantification of toxicants found in

      necrophagous  arthropods  responsible                          Hodecek, J. (2020). Revisiting the

      for  the  death  of  an  individual  in  the                   concept of entomotoxicology.
      absence  of  conventional  toxicological                       Forensic Science International:

      evidence.  The  incorporation  of  DNA                         Synergy, 2, 282-286.
      analysis       along      with      analytical                 https://doi.org/10.1016/j.fsisyn.2020.0

      instrumentation        will    increase     the                9.003

      accuracy        of     entomotoxicological
      analysis.  Rapid  introduction  of  new                         Pacini, T. (2014). The Importance of

      drugs and poisons has a varying effect                         Cooperation in Forensic Sciences:
      on  the  growth  and  development  of                          The Entomotoxicology. Ann Forensic

      necrophagous  insects,  which  requires                        Res Anal 1(2): 1006

      extensive  research  and  instrumental                         https://www.jscimedcentral.com/publi
      analysis  to  determine  the  presence  of                     c/assets/articles/forensic-1-1006.pdf

      the toxicants in arthropods for effective

      analysis.  Entomotoxicology,  being  a                         Chophi, R., Sharma, Spriha.,
      growing  sub-discipline  in  forensic                          Sharma, Sahil. and Singh, R. (2019).

      science,  requires  a  continuous  process                     Forensic entomotoxicology: Current

      of  development  and  validation  of                           concepts, trends and challenges.
      analytical instrumental techniques.                            Journal of Forensic and Legal

                                                                     Medicine, 67, 28-36.
                                                                     https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jflm.2019.07.

                                                                     010















                                       VERITAS VOLUME:4 ISSUE: 1]]></page><page Index="104"><![CDATA[98

         AUTHOR: ANOHA ANN                  UNVEILING THE

                  CHERIAN                   POSTMORTEM TRAITS OF




                                            ASPHYXIAL DEATHS: A



                                            COMPARATIVE ANALYSIS

      DID YOU

      KNOW ??                               INTRODUCTION

         In 19th century British
                                            Asphyxial  death  is  death  caused  by  a  lack  of  oxygen  or
        India, there was believed
                                            excess  of  carbon  dioxide  in  the  body,  which  causes
          to exist a bandit cult
                                            suffocation in the respiratory tract and unconsciousness. In
        named “Thuggee”  who
            were masters of                 asphyxia,  the  process  of  exchanging  air  between  the
       asphyxiation. They mostly            surroundings  and  the  air  sacs  in  the  lungs  is  interrupted,

        used towels and rags as             which results in a lack of oxygen reaching the body's cells.
                 weapon                     There are various types of deaths caused by asphyxia, each

                                            of which exhibits different postmortem characteristics.



       The     various      types    of      Hanging is caused when the individual's body is supported
       asphyxial death are:                  by  a  ligature  around  the  neck,  with  the  body's  weight

                                             applying  pressure,  causing  suffocation  and  death  due  to

          1. Hanging                         asphyxia. There are different types of hanging based on the
          2. Strangulation                   site of a knot of the ligature (typical & atypical hanging),

          3. Drowning                        based  on  the  body  touching  the  ground  (complete  &

                                             incomplete  hanging),  and  based  on  the  manner  of  death
       This article delves into the          (suicidal,  homicidal,  accidental,  judicial,  and  autoerotic

       detailed      discussion      of      hanging).

       different         postmortem
       characteristics  associated           Strangulation  results  in  death  due  to  asphyxia,  where  the

       with        hanging         and       neck  is  compressed  by  a  ligature  or  material  without
       strangulation.                        suspending the body. Strangulation can be of various types

                                             (Ligature Strangulation, Garrotting, Mugging, Bansdola &

                                             Throtting).
                                             The  postmortem  findings  can  assist  in  distinguishing

                                             between hanging and strangulation both before death and
                                             after death.



                                       VERITAS VOLUME:4 ISSUE: 1]]></page><page Index="105"><![CDATA[99


      The  general  findings  in  Ante  Mortem
      Hanging and Strangulation:



         1. Cyanosis is a condition in which a bluish
           colour appears on the skin caused by an

           insufficient  amount  of  oxygen  in  the
           body.

         2. Petechial haemorrhages are blood clots in

           the form of tiny circular dots present on
           the body as a result of haemorrhages.

         3. Ligature marks with neck bruises.
                                                                         Image 2: Strangulation
         4. Bleeding from nostrils and mouth.                            https://dkanderson.com/strangulation-and-
         5. Dribbling of saliva.                                         suffocation/

         6. Hands are clenched.
























                                                                         Image 3: Cyanosis
                                                                         https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cyanosis









                 Image 1: Hanging
                 K S Narayan Murty O P Reddy. (2017b).
                 Essentials of forensic medicine and toxicology.
                 (p. 160). Jaypee








                                                                         Image 4: Petechial hemorrhages
                                                                         https://www.healthline.com/health/petechiae






                                       VERITAS VOLUME:4 ISSUE: 1]]></page><page Index="106"><![CDATA[100


































                                                                         Image 5: Le Facie sympathique
                                                                         “MechanicalAsphyxia1.”https://www.slides
                                                                         hare.net/slideshow/mechanical-asphyxia-
                                                                         1/154304355








      CONCLUSION                                                            REFERENCES



      Postmortem  findings  play  a  vital  role  in                            Asphyxia(2012).Pathology

      differentiating  between  different  types  of                            outlines.com.https://www.p
      asphyxial deaths. Each type of asphyxial death                            athologyoutlines.com/topic/

      has  distinct,  identifiable  features.  Determining                      forensicsasphyxia.html
      the  type  of  asphyxial  death  assists  in

      determining  the  manner,  time,  cause,  and                             Forensic  Analysis  of  Injury

      brutality  of  the  crime.  The  victim's  body  is  a                    and Death by Asphyxiation.
      valuable  piece  of  evidence  that  aids  in                             (2019).  The  TASA  Group.

      investigations.  These  traits  are  analyzed,  and                       https://www.tasanet.com/K
      they  offer  an  understanding  of  the  situation                        nowledge-

      leading to the death, assisting the legal process,                        Center/Articles/ArtMID/47

      guaranteeing  the  proper  enforcement  of  the                           7/ArticleID/338920/Forensi
      law,  and  contributing  to  achieving  justice  for                      c-Analysis-of-Injury-and-

      the individual.                                                           Death-by-Asphyxiation










                                       VERITAS VOLUME:4 ISSUE: 1]]></page><page Index="107"><![CDATA[101


                                            THROUGH THE LENS OF
       AUTHOR: ARPITA PRIYA
                                            JUSTICE: “THE


                                            SIGNIFICANCE OF


      DID YOU                               FORENSIC PHOTOGRAPHY”

      KNOW ??


                                             ABSTRACT
             "A picture is worth a

        thousand words, and this
                                             The photograph is derived from the Greek words 'phos',
        is especially true in crime
                                             which means "light," and 'graphe', meaning "drawing."
           scene photography."
                                             Therefore, photography means drawing with lines. It is
                                             the first thing performed at the scene of a crime. It gives

                                             the whole story in the background of what might have

        INTRODUCTION                         happened. It plays a tremendous role in reconstructing
                                             the crime scene with the help of visual proof captured

                                             and thus helps contribute to a legal outcome. It depicts
        Photography           is      a
                                             minute details that couldn't be identified by human eyes.
        conventional         method.
                                             Not only "photography," but "forensic photographers"
        Forensic  photography  is
                                             also matter. The photographer should have technical as
        as  old  as  a  camera.  The
                                             well as mechanical knowledge.
        first photography attempt
        was  made  by  Thomas

        Wedgwood in 1795.


                                                   Yes,  we  do  apply  'FILTERS'  in  forensic
        Nowadays,           everyone
                                                   photography! But not to enhance or beautify an
        knows                   about
                                                   image;  otherwise,  it  would  be  considered  an
        photography,  but  very
                                                   alteration  in  evidence,  but  we  apply  filters  to
        few  students  know  about
                                                   highlight  and  reveal  the  hidden  evidence.  The
        forensic       photography.
                                                   filters  used  in  forensic  photography  are  physical
        Photography            doesn't
                                                   filters,  unlike  mobile  phones  with  digital  filters.
        mean  just  posting  or
                                                   These filters can't be used to add colors but can
        taking pictures of yourself
                                                   modify  light  through  transmission,  absorption,
        or  nature  by  applying
                                                   and interference.
        'filters'.









                                       VERITAS VOLUME:4 ISSUE: 1]]></page><page Index="108"><![CDATA[102





      Key tips for crime scene photos:                         Merging photography with other techniques:



           A      consistent      and       systematic              DRONES (UAV)

           approach  should  be  maintained.
           Photographs  should  be  taken  along               Photographs  minimize  direct  contact,

           with  the  scale  to  ensure  the  correct          protect      the     evidence,      and      reduce

           measurement  and  details,  which                   contamination  concerns.  It  ensures  the
           could help the investigation officer.               accuracy of the crime scene by providing 3-

                                                               D  mapping.  It  is  easily  and  quickly

           Ambient light should be used to take                deployed  to  far-away  and  unreachable
           photographs.  Flashlights  should  be               regions,  reducing  the  reaction  time  in  an

           avoided, as they could cause shadows                emergency. Drones are accurate devices that

           and  beautification.  Thereby,  not                 give quick details in shallow water. It is an
           ensuring  the  accuracy  and  clearance             economical and cost-efficient device.

           of the evidence.
                                                                    UV, IR, LIGHT AND

           Multiple  photographs  from  different                   FLUORESCENT POWDER

           angles  and  locations  should  be
           captured  by  different  types  of  shots,          UV  light  is  used  in  the  detection  of  blood

           such  as  overall,  mid-range,  close-up,           stains,  biological  fluids,  injuries,  and  bite
           and     evidence-specific       shots,    to        marks, and in cases of document alteration.

           provide  a  logical  story  and  ensure

           completeness by capturing the entire                IR light reveals the hidden details. It is used
           scene and all evidence.                             in    smuggling        scenarios      and     night

                                                               surveillance.



           Neutrality  is  an  essential  key  during          Fluorescent powder can be used to highlight

           crime  scene  photography.  Being                   latent  prints  and  trace  evidence  on  darker

           biased  does  not  ensure  justice,                 surfaces.
           leading to false documentation.

















                                       VERITAS VOLUME:4 ISSUE: 1]]></page><page Index="109"><![CDATA[103

                                                                  Crime  scene  photography  will
             Photography  is  a  basic  task  that  is
                                                                  continue  to  be  essential  in
             performed primarily during a crime
                                                                  investigations and will grow more
             scene  investigation,  no  matter  how
                                                                  significantly       with       ongoing
             an  officer  elaborates  on  the  crime
                                                                  technological improvements.
             scene,  but  a  photograph  plays  a
             crucial  role  in  a  crime  scene

             investigation  as  it  freezes  time  and

             tells   the    story     more     clearly.
                                                                  REFERENCES
             Videography can have poor lighting

             and  focus,  improper  use  of  zoom,
                                                                      AZoLifeSciences. (2022, September
             and even sometimes swiveling of the
                                                                      22). How Important is Crime Scene
             camera.
                                                                      Photography to Forensic
                                                                      Investigations?
             Photographs  can  be  secured  by
                                                                      https://www.azolifesciences.com/art
             creating  a  hash  value  to  maintain
                                                                      icle/How-Important-is-Crime-
             data integrity, ensuring the data and
                                                                      Scene-Photography-to-Forensic-
             details  are  not  tampered  with  or
                                                                      Investigations.aspx
             altered in any way.

                                                                      Alex, J. (2022, May 27). The
             CONCLUSION
                                                                      importance of photography in
                                                                      forensic investigations | PMI
             Photography  is  the  most  efficient
                                                                      Evidence TrackerTM. PMI.
             and  vital  tool  in  crime  scene
                                                                      https://pmievidencetracker.com/202
             photography. It is a straightforward
                                                                      1/03/24/the-importance-of-
             way  for  an  investigation  officer  to
                                                                      photography-in-forensic-
             depict  a  crime  scene,  as  it  gives  a
                                                                      investigations/
             true  and  accurate  record  of  the

             crime  scene  and  tangible  evidence
                                                                      Urbanová, P., Jurda, M., Vojtíšek,
             present  at  the  crime  scene.  It
                                                                      T., & Krajsa, J. (2017). Using
             provides      visual     documentation
                                                                      drone-mounted cameras for on-site
             important           in         analyzing,
                                                                      body documentation: 3D mapping
             reconstructing,       and      presenting
                                                                      and active survey. Forensic Science
             evidence in criminal cases.
                                                                      International, 281, 52–62.
                                                                      https://doi.org/10.1016/j.forsciint.2

                                                                      017.10.027





                                       VERITAS VOLUME:4 ISSUE: 1]]></page><page Index="110"><![CDATA[104




            CONTRIBUTORS













                        S. NO                                     NAME




                            1                                   Sri Ineya K





                           2                                 Deboleena Guha




                           3                                 Priyanka Ghosh




                           4                                    Ansilmary




                           5                              Senatra Naina Silveria





                           6                                  Sreevidya Rejith





                            7                               Rothika Ganapathi




                            8                                   Zeel Pandya



                            9                              Ashwitha Kathiresan





                          10                                    Neha Jain





                          11                                      Roshni




                           12                            Savannah Pieaded Lobo]]></page><page Index="111"><![CDATA[105




            CONTRIBUTORS



















                       S. NO                                    NAME



                         13                              Anoha Ann Cherian




                         14                                    Hamsa J




                         15                               Annie Sherin A




                         16                          Abhinandan Nagabhushana



                         17                              Additiya Sengupta



                         18                                  Vani Gupta




                         19                                  Arpita Priya



                         20                               Ragavi Allakathan



                         21                                Hansen S. Jerem




                         22                              Anashwara Pramod



                         23                                 Keziah Angel




                         24                               Ancila Robinson]]></page><page Index="112"><![CDATA[DEPARTMENT OF FORENSIC SCIENCE



                                         Bi- Annual Publication
































































                  Scan the QR code or Use the URL
                                             ISSN: 2583-7044 (Online)

                                                     Title: Veritas
                         below to share your feedback


                                  https://forms.gle/TxoDBgcw5nn6Gbid7
                                                                                    Vol.4, Issue 1]]></page></pages></Search>